<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peaceable disquisitions which treat of the natural and spiritual man, preaching with the demonstration of the Spirit, praying by the Spirit, assurance, the Arminian grace, possibility of heathens salvation, the reconciliation of Paul and James, the imputation of Christ's righteousness, with other incident matters : in some animadversions on a discourse writ against Dr. Owen's Book of the Holy Spirit / by John Humfrey ...</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12484450</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12484450</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62274</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62274)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 279:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peaceable disquisitions which treat of the natural and spiritual man, preaching with the demonstration of the Spirit, praying by the Spirit, assurance, the Arminian grace, possibility of heathens salvation, the reconciliation of Paul and James, the imputation of Christ's righteousness, with other incident matters : in some animadversions on a discourse writ against Dr. Owen's Book of the Holy Spirit / by John Humfrey ...</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 105 [i.e. 109], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Owen, John, 1616-1683. --  Pneumatologia.</term>
               <term>Clagett, William, 1646-1688. --  Treatise concerning the operations of the Holy Spirit, together with a confutation of some part of Dr. Owen's book, i.e. Pneumatologia.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PEACEABLE DISQUISITIONS. Which Treat
Of <list>
                  <item>The Natural and Spiritual Man.</item>
                  <item>Preaching with the Demonſtration of the Spirit.</item>
                  <item>Praying by the Spirit. Aſſurance.</item>
                  <item>The Arminian Grace. Poſſibility of Heathens Salvation.</item>
                  <item>The reconciliation of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; with other Incident Matters.</item>
               </list> In ſome Animadverſions On a Diſcourſe writ againſt <hi>Dr.</hi> OWEN's <hi>Book of the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN HUMFREY.</p>
            <p>Doing nothing by Partiality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for Thomas Parkhurſt, at the <hi>Three Crowns</hi> and <hi>Bible,</hi> the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62274:2"/>
            <head>Peaceable Diſquiſitions.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the right underſtanding of the Apoſtles <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> man, and of Preaching with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit and of Power.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving met with a Book entituled, <hi>A diſcourſe concerning the operations of the Holy Spirit, in confutation of Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>upon that Subject,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be tempted to make ſome Animadverſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, whether out of <hi>conſent</hi> to the Authour in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, or <hi>diſſent</hi> in others: for a Reſentment to ſee how nothing almoſt of this Doctor's can come abroad (though in matters onely practical, and not polemical) but there is a generation of men upon the wing ready to fly upon it, as if they were never ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unleſs they could render that worthy perſon quite uſeleſs to the Church in all his Labours, is enough to put me upon it.</p>
               <p>I do acknowledge that this freſh Antagoniſt of his does appear to me to be a man of very ſmart abilities, and of a maſculine ſtyle, regarding his conceptions without affectation of words, for which I value him, and I am beholding to him for the pleaſure which he hath given me in the liberality of his notions: yet do I think really that he and his conſorts, ſuch as the Authour of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity,</hi> and the like, are to be blamed for two things.</p>
               <p>The one is, their <hi>Immorality</hi> (as I judge of it) in treating ſuch men as Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> as they do, with ſo much ſlighting and contempt, and that without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62274:3"/>either any <hi>regret</hi> of conſcience for the injuſtice and wrong (which to ſpeak unworthily of the worthy muſt be) or <hi>due reflexion</hi> upon their own mortality and imperfections: And who are we, that enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to compariſon?</p>
               <p>The other is, their intrenchment on <hi>things ſacred</hi> with the ſame boldneſs and liberty of <hi>ſarcaſme</hi> as in <hi>things common;</hi> whereby in their endeavor to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Party, and this Doctor to ſcorn, they do bring Religion it ſelf into a lighter eſtimation. I ſpeak this chiefly in regard to ſome Books writ by way of Dialogue; for I find this Gentleman reſtraining himſelf one place upon that account.</p>
               <p>I will ſuppoſe this Authour to have ſtudied Divinity about <hi>Ten</hi> years, allotting his former life for other accompliſhments, and the Dr. to have ſtudied theſe things <hi>Forty</hi> years: I do think now, if this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had had a little miſgiving in his mind at the conſideration of this imparity, and thereupon expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if not more <hi>Reſpect,</hi> yet ſome more <hi>Modeſty</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Dr. it would have caſt ſome better grace on his undertaking.</p>
               <p>In this Preface, the Dr. belike having ſaid in one of his Books, ſpeaking to the people, <hi>You are in a miſerable condition, if you have all this while relyed upon the authority of men in heavenly things.</hi> This <hi>ſeems to imply</hi> (ſaies the Gentleman) <hi>that all men are in a ſtate of damnation who rely upon the honeſty and wiſdom of their Spiritual Guides in matters of Faith: But — I hope ſome of thoſe do ſo firmly believe the Truth, upon the Teſtimony of God's Miniſters, as to live according to it; which if they do, God forhid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62274:3"/>that I ſhould ſay they are in a damnable condition.</hi> If I may take my conjecture from this leſs virulent paſſage in the <hi>Preface,</hi> into what odious conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions the Drs. words are like to be wiredrawn ſtill throughout the <hi>Book;</hi> it will be to no purpoſe I count for me to go about the redeeming the Dr. from abuſes, which are ſo multiplied upon him of all ſorts, and on all occaſions, as pleaſes theſe Authours pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate minds: but to attend rather other matters, which ſhall adminiſter occaſion for the ſtriking of light, or the free purſuit and improvement of Truth, that ſhall offer it ſelf as we go along, to our mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual edification.</p>
               <p>This is my opinion, that Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> is a man of that eminent Learning, and all ſorts of Worth, both as a <hi>Sholar</hi> and <hi>Civil Gentleman,</hi> that he deſerves other Treatment from theſe men, and is above my Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>In this Book, after the Preface, we have an <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> and Seven <hi>Chapters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Introduction preſents us with a diſſertation about one place of the Apoſtle, which is much can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſed in the Arminian Controverſie, and does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore require our firſt attendance, The words are theſe, <hi>The natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs to him: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the <hi>Natural man,</hi> this worthy perſon under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands one that is governed onely by <hi>Reaſon:</hi> and by the <hi>Spiritual man,</hi> he underſtands him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives and judges of things by the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> The
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62274:4"/>natural man now (ſaies he) receives not thoſe Doctrines of Chriſtianity, the truth whereof is not diſcoverable by natural reaſon, becauſe they are <hi>fooliſhneſs to him,</hi> in that they cannot be proved hereby: and he <hi>cannot know them,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> that is, becauſe they are made known onely by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> which the natural man either hath not, or rejects. See here an interpretation which looks grave and ſolid as well as ingenious; but whether it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the right or no, we are to judge by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of it with the place. In the twelfth verſe before the Text, the Apoſtle ſaies, That <hi>we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Spirit of God, that we may know the things,</hi> which he had before called <hi>the deep things of God:</hi> And in the verſe next after the Text he tells us, <hi>The ſpiritual man judgeth all things.</hi> It is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent then that the <hi>ſpiritual man</hi> in the one verſe, and he that hath <hi>received the Spirit</hi> in the other, muſt be one: But the Revelation of the Scriptures <hi>without</hi> us to judge of things by, and the Spirit of God <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> either inſpiring theſe things, or operating on the mind to underſtand them, are two things, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, if the <hi>Spiritual man</hi> be him that hath <hi>received the Spirit</hi> within <hi>to know the things of God,</hi> it muſt not be him that hath onely received the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and rejects them not. Beſides this, a man may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Scriptures as the Revelation of God, and judge of Doctrines by it, and be much skill'd in the letter of it, as the <hi>Socinians</hi> are, and yet not receive the great myſtery thereof, <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh:</hi> And how does the <hi>ſpiritual man judge of all things,</hi> if this be the ſpiritual man? Nay, how can it be ſaid of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62274:4"/>him, that <hi>he is judged of none,</hi> ſeeing as he <hi>judges all things</hi> by theſe Scriptures, ſo is he <hi>judged</hi> of all, in what he holds, by the ſame?</p>
               <p>There is another interpretation therefore (for it is another, and this Authour muſt not compound his with it) to be laid down in the ſecond place. By the <hi>natural man,</hi> which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we may underſtand him who hath onely the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or reaſonable ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <hi>Adam;</hi> and by the ſpiritual man him who hath received the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or that Spirit which is from Chriſt. <hi>The firſt man Adam was made a living ſoul, the ſecond Adam was made a quickening ſpirit.</hi> This Spirit, as it was promiſed to be poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men in the <hi>latter daies,</hi> which was the time of the New Teſtament; ſo do we find it given ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily at their Baptiſm and Confirmation; as we read in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and as we find in this Epiſtle. <hi>The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit with all.</hi> Where we have this <hi>Spirit</hi> given, and that to every one: and the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That <hi>manifeſtation</hi> poſſibly might be by ſome <hi>Shechinah,</hi> ſometimes on the heads of the baptized: but the certain meaning appears in the following verſes, to be by the miraculous gifts then poured out. Among which gifts, one of them was the <hi>Diſcernment</hi> of myſteries, <hi>Spirits,</hi> that is, Doctrines; and ſo is the Spirit given and received (we are to ſuppoſe) in this place. <hi>We have received the Spirit of God,</hi> ſaies the Text, to this effect, <hi>That we may know the things which he hath freely given us.</hi> The whole meaning then is thus, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the man who had not this Spirit then poured on him,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62274:5"/>could not diſcern thoſe things of the Spirit as others of them could, who had it, becauſe theſe <hi>hidden things</hi> were diſcoverable by that miraculous gift; and he having not the <hi>Gift</hi> to diſcern them, muſt judge of them by <hi>natural reaſon</hi> onely, and ſo they were <hi>fooliſhneſs to him;</hi> when as to them who had it, they appeared the <hi>Power of God,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom of God.</hi> And of this <hi>Spiritual man</hi> ſo interpreted, that is, the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red man, one that had the <hi>mind of Christ</hi> in the laſt verſe, and that <hi>received the Spirit</hi> in the tenth, for this effect, the diſcernment of theſe things; it is eaſie to underſtand how he could <hi>judge all things,</hi> and be <hi>judged of none,</hi> in regard that this inſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in could be diſcernable to himſelf onely; and ſo the text and context, and the whole chapter ſhall be made to agree throughout, one verſe with another. Nevertheleſs there is one inconvenience this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is liable to, as will make it to be refuſed by moſt men, when we have ſaid all we can. It is this, that if this be the meaning, then muſt this whole place be applicable onely to thoſe Chriſtians in the Apoſtles daies, and no Chriſtian at this time can be concerned: That is, if this be the ſenſe, then is there no man now that hath <hi>received the Spirit of God, that he may know the things of God;</hi> no <hi>ſpiritual man</hi> now in the true ſenſe of this place, but all muſt be <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> men onely, as <hi>having not the Spirit</hi> according to this interpretation; when yet the <hi>giving of the Spirit</hi> otherwhere, and in the ſenſe of other Texts, is a branch of the <hi>New Covenant;</hi> and <hi>he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt</hi> (St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies in another place) <hi>is none of his.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62274:5"/>
               <p>There is a third Interpretation therefore, that by the <hi>Natural</hi> man and <hi>Spiritual</hi> man we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate</hi> and <hi>Regenerate</hi> man, that is, one that hath not, and one that hath <hi>received the Spirit</hi> to the ordinary effects of it, which is illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſanctification. And this is the moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Opinion and Interpretation which is received by our Divines, and ſo taken up by Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elaborately he hath improved it: ſo little reaſon hath this Gentleman, or any others, to make any aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault on him for that matter. When the unre<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man then in the Text is ſaid not <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> things of the Spirit,</hi> or Doctrines of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he <hi>cannot</hi> (that is, morally cannot) receive <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> meaning of our Divines in general is this, that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> does not, or cannot receive or diſcern them ſo as to <hi>ſavour</hi> them, or <hi>reliſh</hi> them; he does not, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not embrace them in his heart, as good to him, or ſo, as to lead his life according to them. In ſhort, he cannot receive them ſo as to <hi>apply</hi> them. And this is a Truth never to be gainſaid by this man; though which of the three Interpretations is to be preferr'd, I paſs not my own judgment.</p>
               <p>Let us hear this Authour's Objections. The Doctor (ſaies he) does grant that an unregenerate man may <hi>aſſent</hi> to the truth of the things of God; and if he can aſſent to them, he can ſee a conformity in them to God's Attributes, and a ſuitableneſs to the ends of the Goſpel; and if he can ſee this, then will they not appear <hi>fooliſhneſs to him;</hi> and conſequently he <hi>can know them.</hi> Every one will anſwer to this. There is a <hi>Speculative</hi> and a <hi>Practical</hi> knowledge.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62274:6"/>When our Divines ſay, the unregenerate man cannot know theſe things, they underſtand it of a <hi>Practical</hi> knowledge; he does know them <hi>ſpecial lively,</hi> but he hath no <hi>vital, experimental</hi> knowledge of them: And when the reaſon is given in the Text, becauſe they are <hi>ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> we muſt expound <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, i. e.</hi> by the aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this third Interpretation. The <hi>Natural</hi> man does not receive, know, or diſcern theſe <hi>things of God,</hi> as able (I account) to <hi>apply</hi> them, becauſe they are diſcerned onely by a <hi>ſupernatural aſſistance of the Holy Ghost;</hi> which they, having not, cannot do it. I will anſwer farther. The Spirit may be given and received to divers effects: on her for illumination and conviction, or for converſion and ſanctification. If the <hi>Natural</hi> man, who is one without the Spirit, hath not the Spirit at all to <hi>illuminate</hi> and <hi>convince</hi> him, he <hi>believes</hi> not the Doctrines of Chriſt, though he <hi>hears</hi> them. <hi>There is no man can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord but by the Holy Ghost;</hi> and while he in his heart <hi>believes</hi> them not, they are indeed to him but <hi>fooliſhneſs;</hi> when if he hath the Spirit but to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten and to convince him, he may dogmatically receive them, going ſo far; and yet until he hath the Spirit alſo to <hi>convert</hi> him and <hi>ſanctifie</hi> him, he cannot <hi>diſcern</hi> them (I muſt ſtill ſay) ſo, as to <hi>apply</hi> them to his <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are three Interpretations then propoſed to them who pleaſe to ſtrive for maſtery: I have but one Note more to add out of this Authour. <hi>By being ſpiritually diſcerned</hi> (ſaies he, ſpeaking of <hi>theſe things</hi> in the Text) <hi>is meant their being known, understood,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62274:6"/>and judged of by the revelation and testimony of the Spirit.</hi> Thus much is right, and muſt be agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by all three Interpretations; onely their difference then alſo muſt be laid down. This <hi>revelation</hi> or <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> therefore, is either <hi>external,</hi> or <hi>internal.</hi> The firſt Opinion (which is this Author's) will have this revelation <hi>external,</hi> and ſo ſhall he that hath the <hi>Scriptures</hi> onely, be accounted to have the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and to diſcern theſe ſpiritual things. The other two Opinions will have this teſtimony or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>internal;</hi> ſo that without the Spirit's opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>within,</hi> the man is to be held a <hi>Natural man,</hi> and not to underſtand <hi>theſe things.</hi> This <hi>internal</hi> revelation of the Spirit then, is either <hi>extraordinary</hi> in the miraculous gifts and diſcernment of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive</hi> times; and the ſecond Opinion is, that the place is to be underſtood of theſe gifts, and ſuch workings of the Spirit as do not belong now to <hi>ours:</hi> or it is <hi>ordinary</hi> in the work of illumination and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, which ſtill continue in the world: and the third Opinion (which is the Drs.) reſts in this, as of moſt concern to us, and moſt eaſie of admiſſion.</p>
               <p>There is a fourth Interpretation. By the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be underſtood the <hi>Senſual</hi> man; and by the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>intellectual</hi> contemplative man. The Platoniſts do diſtinguiſh their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſome of our Platonical Divines do favour this Expoſition. To confirm it, there is that Text in <hi>Jude</hi> may be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, where the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſo tranſlated, <hi>ſenſual, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Spirit,</hi> with other places where <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are oppoſed. This Note by the way I take up however, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are indeed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62274:7"/>the ſame: But this interpretation I think too extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to the firſt, which is our Authors; for theſe mens <hi>ſpiritual man</hi> is no more than his <hi>natural man;</hi> and I am ſatisfied with him, that no man of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt attainment by contemplation can be able to find out any of theſe things in the text which depend on Gods Soveraign Will, and can be diſcovered only by his Spirit. For, <hi>As no man knoweth the things of a man</hi> (ſaies the text) <hi>ſave the ſpirit of a man which is in him; even ſo the things of God knoweth no man but the Spirit of God.</hi> Theſe things of God are (I ſay) the arbitrary councils of God's will for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man by his grace in and through Jeſus Chriſt, which lies not within the ſcheam of Nature, and come not therefore within the ken of humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; unleſs they be made known to us either by inſpiration of them into our ſelves, or by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, through the Spirit, by others.</p>
               <p>There may be haply more Interpretations than theſe (for I conſult not Commentators): but if any be apt to mingle the two former into one, for confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the third, becauſe it is Dr. <hi>Owens,</hi> I do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſuch, to betray a precipitate diſaffection, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a ponderous judgement. I know that the firſt and ſecond (this Authors, and the Friendly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baters) may be made uſe of to confute the third, which is the received interpretation, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors: but ſo may the third and ſecond be uſed to confute this Authors: and yet that will neither make the firſt and ſecond, nor the ſecond and third to be the ſame. That interpretation which gives ſuch a ſenſe of the Chapter as makes the <hi>receiving the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62274:7"/>there applicable only to the Chriſtians in the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times,</hi> cannot be the ſame with that which gives ſuch a ſenſe of it as makes it applicable to Chriſtians <hi>now,</hi> whether all of them, regenerate and unregenerate who have but their Bibles, as this man will have it, or thoſe only who are partakers of it to the effect of <hi>Regeneration,</hi> according to Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us look the Gentlemans Introduction now again over, and we ſhall find that the braggery of that Interpretation which he hath advanced to confute Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> does lye herein, that every one who hath the Scriptures, and does not reject them, muſt have <hi>the Spirit</hi> in the Text to <hi>diſcern the things of God,</hi> and the Doctor muſt be a very proud man who does number himſelf among <hi>ſuch,</hi> and will allow the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> only to know them. This muſt be ſhewn by all means, what an <hi>abſurd</hi> perſon the Doctor is, who will have an <hi>almighty, irreſiſtible, new light</hi> brought into the ſoul by the Holy Ghoſt (that is, a work of illumination on the mind, and converſion on the heart) to enable a man to <hi>diſcern theſe things,</hi> when by <hi>the Spirit</hi> according to him we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the outward revelation of the Word only, which all have, to enable them to diſcern the ſame.</p>
               <p>There is one notion for all this, which is much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated by him, that ſeems to verge upon a mixture of the two firſt Interpretations, by ſetching in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the ſecond into his, which upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of corroborating, is but ſome confounding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf firſt, for confutation of the Doctor. <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>propoſes the demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power to judge of the</hi> truth <hi>of the Goſpel; and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62274:8"/>he alſo propoſeth the comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual to judge of the</hi> ſenſe <hi>of the Doctrines of it.</hi> Again, <hi>Things that are ſpiritually diſcerned are thoſe which be diſcernable only by the revelation of the Spirit. That is, by the teſtimony of the Spirit in miracles as to the</hi> truth <hi>of them, and by comparing one divine revelation with another, as to the</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>of them.</hi> I love the Author for this, becauſe, I muſt confeſs, it ſeems to me to be very neatly ſpoken; and yet it is but a tale when he hath ſaid it. The Apoſtle diſtinguiſhes not the <hi>truth</hi> of the <hi>things of God</hi> in the Text and the <hi>meaning</hi> of them. 'Tis he makes the diſtinction, and puts it on the Apoſtle, as if he intended that which came not once into his mind: Nor does the Apoſtle <hi>propoſe</hi> theſe two ways of <hi>diſcerning things ſpiritually,</hi> but himſelf <hi>propoſes</hi> them. I do not think the Apoſtle to be ſo double mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to underſtand <hi>two</hi> things by this <hi>one</hi> expreſſion, <hi>ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> If he intended by it that the <hi>truth</hi> of the things revealed was <hi>diſcerned</hi> by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Spirit given thereunto by <hi>miracles,</hi> he intended not by it that the <hi>meaning</hi> of them is diſcerned by the teſtimony of <hi>Scripture.</hi> And <hi>e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> if he intended the later, he meant not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. The Apoſtle, I believe, had but one meaning, though theſe two things be true aſunder. There is no man can be ſure that by the <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit</hi> in this Chapter, and the <hi>comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual,</hi> the Apoſtle intended two things, or two wayes of that Spirits teſtimony: it is more likely that the later expreſſion does <hi>de induſtria</hi> expound the former. To wit, that when we find out
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62274:8"/>any truth or doctrine by comparing one Scripture with another, this is the <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the place; which I ſhall have occaſion to ſuppoſe again by and by, in regard to another Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If they are <hi>two</hi> ſorts of teſtimony, no man can be ſure that he intended them both (I ſay ſtill) by that <hi>one</hi> explanation. And who can tell moreover whether the Apoſtle meant, by his <hi>comparing ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things with ſpiritual,</hi> the comparing one <hi>inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> with another (which belongs to the ſecond): or one <hi>Scripture</hi> with another, that is the revelations of the <hi>New</hi> with thoſe of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> (which is proper to the firſt interpretation). The man who had a Revelation within muſt have the <hi>truth</hi> of it and <hi>meaning</hi> both confirmed to him by that inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that to diſtinguiſh of the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> of a doctrine inſpired (that is as to ſuch) is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of no ſignification: And as for thoſe who judge of any doctrine by the Scriptures, they are but rightly to underſtand the <hi>meaning,</hi> and they have the <hi>truth</hi> by that underſtanding. Where the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Doctrine is divine, the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> are one another. As for the confirmation of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by miracles, and more particularly by the effuſion of Gifts in the Primitive times, it does not belong to this Author's, but the ſecond interpretation.</p>
               <p>And from hence ariſes another objection againſt the Doctor, It is from the <hi>demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> we read of in the fourth verſe, by which, this quick Divine (I ſuppoſe) after the famous Author of that book entituled the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> does un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the miraculous operation of the Spirit in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62274:9"/>thoſe times. When the Apoſtle preached the Goſpel at firſt, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt fell</hi> on the hearers, and they ſpake with tongues, underhood myſteries, and could do miracles. This was an undenyable teſtimony to the divinity of their Doctrine, ſo that no man can Preach (out of doubt) with ſuch <hi>demonſtration</hi> now in our dayes. If this then be the meaning of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in that verſe, it muſt be the meaning of it in the verſes following (that is to judge tightly, and the defect of this ready man is here, that he hit not on our intimation before). Conſequently, as this <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit</hi> (if it be ſo) is <hi>by</hi> thoſe miraculous gifts: the <hi>receiving</hi> the Spirit there muſt be <hi>in thoſe gifts,</hi> and particularly the gift of diſcerning, ſo the ſpiritual man muſt be him that <hi>had</hi> that gift, the Natural man him that had it <hi>not,</hi> whereby the one could <hi>judge of all things</hi> (that is, thoſe things in the Text), the other could not <hi>know them,</hi> upon that account. And this is both againſt the Authors, and the Doctors interpretation. The Doctor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the Text ſo as no man can <hi>diſcern the things of God ſpiritually,</hi> unleſs he be regenerate: this Gentleman to oppoſe this, will have all underſtanding Chriſtians be able to underſtand them <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have the revelation of the ſpirit in the Scriptures (and why not <hi>demonſtrate</hi> them ſo by the Spirit likewiſe); And yet is he unhappily lead (I apprehend by the Friendly Debater) to give ſuch an expoſition of one of the verſes of this Chapter, as the reſt being carried on accordingly, his own inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation and the Doctors both are quite gone: That is, when this ingenious man hath offered ſo handſom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62274:9"/>a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of this Text as to render the place gratefully applicable to all Chriſtians, and in ſo much larger a capacity than the Doctor (as the unregenerate are more than the regenerate) he does by one inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant leading conceſſion fall into <hi>theirs,</hi> as does make this place proper only to the primitive times. Such need have they who are too forward in charging others with inconſiſtencies, to look to themſelves, that their own writings be conſiſtent, with a mature judgement, and the fear of God, in doing <hi>to</hi> others as they would be done to <hi>by</hi> others.</p>
               <p>I will therefore now turn to ſome words of the Friendly Debater himſelf, and in the mean time make this ſtand. The revelation which a man hath from <hi>without,</hi> and the underſtanding accordingly this <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Spirit</hi> by having the Scriptures, and judging all things by them, is <hi>one</hi> thing: and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation which he hath from <hi>within,</hi> and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>receiving the Spirit</hi> by the miraculous gift of diſcernment, by which he judges of theſe things, ſo as indeed he can be <hi>judged of none,</hi> is <hi>another.</hi> Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let this Author cleave to his own Expoſition, and forſake the other; or let him forſake his own, and cleave to the other. And hereby ſhall all argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments gathered from this place of Scripture, about any point in diſpute in our dayes (ſuch as are the doctrines of free grace, and free will, and of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Authors Book, (the operations of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit) be laid to ſleep, and give us no trouble.</p>
               <p>The words I mean of the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> are theſe, becauſe they afford us ſome farther neceſſary matter.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62274:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Aſſembly of Divines when they direct men how to perform their Miniſtry doe not ſpeak ſo in their Directory as to be underſtood; ſince they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not propheſie, nor ſpeak with tongues, nor demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their doctrine by miracles, as the Apoſtles did. I would gladly know what they mean by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the truth in the demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of power; I am apt to think it would puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle a new Aſsembly to tell us in plain words what they intended by that phraſe. Let me deſire you not to uſe words without ſenſe belonging to them, and to entreat your Miniſter that he would here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after forbear to pray to God, he may ſpeak ſo as no body now can hope to do. I wonder at you, that you ſhould not diſcern the Apoſtle ſpeaks there of the wonderful work of the Holy Ghoſt. I doubt your Miniſter is not inlightned, becauſe he doth not inſtruct you better in the Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not here diſlike this liberty of conception in ſo well-ſtudied an Interpreter of Scripture as I take that Writer to be, that when the Apoſtle ſpeaks of his own Preaching in the <hi>demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of power</hi> he accounts it to be underſtood of that confirmation of the Chriſtian Doctrine by the miraculous gifts as was in thoſe times: yet when he proceeds to ſo univerſal an adventure as to forbid every Miniſter to uſe that expreſſion henceforward any more in his prayer, the ſingularity offends.</p>
               <p>In the Liturgy we have theſe words in a prayer. <hi>Almighty God who alone workeſt great miracles, ſend down upon our Biſhops and Curates the helpful Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thy gr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace.</hi> This expreſſion does allude to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62274:10"/>miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt at firſt on the Apoſtles, when there <hi>appeared eleven tongues and f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r on ea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of them;</hi> and the Church does pray here in this ſenſe, that God who wrought that great <hi>marvel</hi> on the Apoſtles in ſending down his Spirit and gifts at firſt, in that extraordinary manner and way as he did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for ſitting them for their Office, would be pleaſed to vouchſafe the grace and gifts of the ſame Spirit on our preſent Miniſters (whether ſuperiour or inferiour) in that <hi>ordinary</hi> manner and meaſure full, as is ſit for ſuch as do ſucceed them in that great imployment. I may preſume (I doubt not) to ſay the ſame here, that ſuppoſe the Apoſtles Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit and of power</hi> to lye only in thoſe miraculous gifts or effects of the Holy Ghoſt now ceaſed, the Miniſter while he prayes to God for his bleſſing that he may preach ſo, is to be underſtood in the like alluſion and meaning: to wit, that as God enabled the Apoſtles in their time to ſpeak in the <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit and of power,</hi> whatſoever that was; ſo he would aſſiſt him in ſuch a way and manner now as is but ſutable to the preſent work and his ordinary operation.</p>
               <p>Thus much I ſay upon ſuppoſition of our ſecond, and this <hi>Debaters</hi> Interpretation: but I muſt confeſs I do not find my ſelf convinced in the reading the Text, that this interpretation is indubitable. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (at leaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for Dr. <hi>Owens,</hi> and his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) from the place againſt it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I ſee not any thing that will reſtrain our ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſity to that meaning, and we are not to be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in our allowances to the thoughts of others,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62274:11"/>who keep to the analogy of faith without cogent reaſon.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>demonſtratiin of the Spirit and of power</hi> is oppoſed to the <hi>excellency of ſpeech,</hi> or <hi>enticing words of mans wiſdom.</hi> But the Apoſtles ſpeaking with tongues or his miraculous gifts does not oppoſe the eloquence of man or excellency of words, but rather agree with it. That which does in the moſt direct ſenſe oppoſe the excellency of ſpeech and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing words of mans wiſdom, is plain truth which the Spirit teaches.</item>
                  <item>3. The Apoſtle proceeding on in the Chapter ſpeaks not of himſelf only, but of the whole Church. <hi>Now we have received not the ſpirit of the world, but the Spirit which is of God, that we might know the things which are freely given to us of God.</hi> That which all the faithful do know by the Spirit as well as the Apoſtles, cannot be miraculous or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary. Such is the demonſtration here. Or thus, That which is <hi>common</hi> to all the faithful, and not <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>primitive</hi> times, or to any <hi>particular</hi> perſon, cannot be miraculous or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. Such is the <hi>receiving the Spirit</hi> here, and conſequently the <hi>demonſtration</hi> of it.</item>
                  <item>4. Thoſe things the Holy Ghoſt teaches a man by comparing one thing with another, as ſpiritual things with Spirituals, which is by way of ſtudy and diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reaſon, are not demonſtrated in a way miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and extraordinary, belonging only to the Apoſtles and not other Miniſters of Chriſt: But ſuch was the Apoſtles ſpeaking here, <hi>Which things alſo we ſpeak, not in the words which mans wiſdom teacheth, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62274:11"/>which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. The following compariſon between the <hi>natural</hi> man and the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> man, that one receives or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes not the things of God as diſagreeing to his judgement, and the other does, ſeems more aptly to be underſtood as it is ordinarily of the regenerate and unregenerate, than of the extraordinarily inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red only, unto which this moſt curious Interpreters thoughts muſt lead him.</item>
                  <item>6. In the laſt place, I humbly offer an interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this expreſſion, which if it be not the very meaning of the Text, as much of that which is ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged here ſeems to atteſt: yet will it be ſufficient (I hope) to juſtifie our Prelates, Univerſities, Doctors, with the moſt of the Miniſters of the Church, as well as the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and the more plain and honeſt meaning Country-Preachers in their uſing the ſame ſo ordinarily as they do in their prayers. It is this: To ſpeak in the <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit</hi> is to deliver the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truth of Scripture, or the plain ſenſe of the Spirit in Scripture, in oppoſition to humane conceit or invention: and to ſpeak ſo is to ſpeak
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62274:12"/>in <hi>Power,</hi> becauſe a man may expect that aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt to accompany ſuch Preaching which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not upon other.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Preaching of the Croſs is to them that periſh fooliſhneſs, but unto us which are ſaved it is the power of God. I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the power of God unto ſalvation to every one that believes. Ye received it not as the word of men, but as it is in truth the word of God.</hi> The receiving the word as the word of God and not of man, is the <hi>receiving it in power,</hi> and the preaching it accordingly ſo, is the <hi>preaching it in power;</hi> and what that power is does follow, <hi>Which effectually worketh in you that believe. Our Goſpel came unto you not in word only, but alſo in power and in the Holy Ghoſt. This is my Covenant with them, My Spirit which is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, and of thy ſeed, for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62274:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Subſtance or Contents of the Authors four firſt Chapters, wherein I make my ſelf concerned but little farther.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Return to the Doctors Oppoſer, and I come now from his Introduction to his Book. Of this Book there are two parts. The firſt is to ſhew us what the Scriptures hold forth concerning the Spirits ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. The ſecond is to confute many <hi>pernicious</hi> Doctrines of Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi> The firſt and ſecond both is indeed to do this: but the ſecond ſhall do it all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And this part he hath <hi>reſerved,</hi> I ſuppoſe, to come out hereafter.</p>
               <p>The firſt part then having this ſubject, The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits Operations, does contain ſeven Chapters.</p>
               <p>In his firſt Chapter he explains to us what he means by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and by its <hi>Operations.</hi> The word <hi>Spirit</hi> (ſaies he) ſignifies three things. The <hi>Mind,</hi> the <hi>Temper of the mind,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and he underſtands it of the laſt. I have two things to ſay here. The one is, as to his ſecond ſignification: The temper or diſpoſition of the Mind, is either of <hi>Nature</hi> only, and belongs to the <hi>Spirit of man</hi> within him; or of <hi>Grace,</hi> and belongs to the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> that works it. Of this Temper, the Author muſt be underſtood to ſpeak, when he ſpeaks of the Spirit of <hi>Faith, Fear</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> The other is, that there are more ſignifications of the word <hi>Spirit</hi> than theſe, which himſelf knows. <hi>Every ſpirit which confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62274:13"/>ſeth Chriſt,</hi> in <hi>John,</hi> is (I think) as much as <hi>every Doctrine.</hi> Which by the way does put me in mind to ſay thus much, that when this Author comes to ſpeak of things which are common heads, and only require a grave and comprehenſive Divine to marſhal them, he does methinks appear to me ſo lank, as I cannot tell well whether that which he ſaies be <hi>ſolid</hi> or no, becauſe I am ſure it is not <hi>full:</hi> though when he falls upon ſeveral particular things, he ſeems to look through them well. By the <hi>operations</hi> of the Spirit he underſtands (and defines them) <hi>thoſe which are on the mind, to cauſe certain qualities, promiſed in the Goſpel, and continued in all ages.</hi> I have two things therefore to ſay here likewiſe. One is, that though this were never ſo much too ſhort, there is no body in the main of what is ſaid, is like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict him. Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> underſtands the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as he does; and by the <hi>Operations</hi> of it, what he does. And why then will he fall foul on the Dr.? When he agrees with him in the ſubſtance, what need is there he ſhould <hi>purſue a flea</hi> in the circumſtances of words only, or variety of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? Another is, that where he excepts at the Doctor for alluding in his words to ſome Texts that ſpeak of miraculous gifts, and ſo cannot be applied to us, and alſo for a critical note (he had before) on the Hebrew word <hi>[put on him] Iſa.</hi> 42.1. from whence he collects that in Gods giving us the effects of his Spirit, the Spirit it ſelf is alſo given, I will compound with this Author. The Doctor ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his critical note to the Spirit of the Prophets, and this man ſhall let the Doctor ſpeak but the ſame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62274:13"/>things by way of alluſion to Scripture (whether they be proved thereby or not), which other Divines do ſpeak and affirm ordinarily without that alluſion.</p>
               <p>In his ſecond Chapter he ſhews us <hi>what theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are, for the producing of which, the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is given;</hi> which he undertakes to do here from that Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. where, After two parables of the man asking <hi>three Loaves</hi> for his Friend, and of a <hi>Son</hi> asking <hi>Bread</hi> of a Father, our Saviour tells us, that <hi>God will give his holy Spirit to thoſe that ask him.</hi> From hence he gathers that the effects for which God gives his Spirit are ſuch as are <hi>needful,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>Bread</hi> the Son and the Friend asks: and <hi>profitable,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Fiſh</hi> and <hi>Egg</hi> alſo is given. Here he tells, that our need is to be meaſured by the end; That the end is our ſalvation. Conſequently, the Spirits operations on the mind are to produce all thoſe effects as are neceſſary to eternal life. Theſe are Faith, Knowledge; All Vertue or graces which make us practical Chriſtians; and Perſeverance. Here are his <hi>needful</hi> effects: then his <hi>profitable,</hi> and not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> are degrees of Goodneſs, which are more highly ſo; or degrees of Knowledge, that are leſs profitable. Here he diſcourſes whether God does give the Spirit for theſe things <hi>profitable</hi> upon our asking; and tells us, God may give us things better or more ſutable, and ſo deny them. Then he ſhews us how the Spirit is prayed for in the Lords prayer, becauſe when we ask for any grace or vertue, we ask for him to work it. In the whole then of this Chapter we have nothing againſt the Doctor, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62274:14"/>the Doctor againſt him, but a good Sermon I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we have, which he might have preached ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and adapts it to this occaſion; which makes it look (though well, yet) feat, and unlike a beaten Divine; who in ſhewing what the effects of Gods Spirit are, would have caſt them into ſome proper and fuller order, and then proved them by Scripture, and quite let alone this Sermon.</p>
               <p>His third Chapter is about <hi>Regeneration,</hi> which he makes room for by an Objection, that this will be thought but a <hi>lame account</hi> of thoſe qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are needful to ſalvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeing one thing moſt neceſſary thereunto is omitted, and that is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation. And here then muſt Regeneration be brought in and ſhewn us, that it is not ſuch a thing as Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> makes it, but is comprized in his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral graces and vertues. <hi>Regeneration</hi> then as <hi>a ſtate</hi> (he defines it) <hi>is to become a ſincere Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And here, though one might well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a little more accuracy in a definition, there is no body like to differ with him upon the matter. The <hi>Doctor</hi> may uſe other terms and expreſſions, and <hi>he</hi> uſes theſe, but they <hi>both</hi> intend the ſame thing. This is certain, <hi>He that doth righteouſneſs is born of God.</hi> The Doctor belike hath ſaid, that Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a <hi>proper</hi> Term, and he will prove it to be <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical.</hi> Be it ſo. The Doctor muſt be candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood then, that he means, it is a <hi>proper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor.</hi> To wit, that there is ſuch a ſecret and powerful work of the ſoul ſignified thereby, as does bring in a new diſpoſion into the <hi>inner man,</hi> as well
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62274:14"/>as reforms the outward life, which is, that only in effect he contends for. <hi>Let them grant</hi> (ſaies the Doctor) <hi>that their Moral reformation of life does proceed from a Spiritual reformation of our nature, the difference will be at an end.</hi> And what ſaies this Author? He anſwers. <hi>This difference is at an end before it began, for we have alwaies granted it.</hi> And why is the difference up then, that hath no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or cauſe for it? The Doctor is perhaps too <hi>warm</hi> in the <hi>alluſion,</hi> but the meaning is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the ſame with his, who is as it were quite <hi>cool</hi> and off from it. There is indeed one point as to the <hi>manner</hi> of the Spirits <hi>operation,</hi> wherein theſe two Champions will differ, but that belongs to another Chapter. Here he ſpeaks of Regeneration only as a <hi>ſtate,</hi> and therefore I pray let him be quiet yet a while, till he comes thither.</p>
               <p>In his fourth Chapter he laies down the <hi>ſeveral graces of the holy Spirit;</hi> which having done <hi>once</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I cannot apprehend it to be momentous in his making <hi>two</hi> Chapters of it. Theſe graces then again are Faith, Teachableneſs in order to it, All Chriſtian vertues, The improvement of them, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in them, Perſeverance to the end. To this we oppoſe nothing, and there is no diſſention with the Doctor. The Doctor (or another) perhaps would have marſhalled theſe things otherwiſe: but that all theſe are the operations of Gods Spirit, or ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects for which the Holy Ghoſt is to be implored, is beyond diſpute amongſt us. What he hath thruſt in here upon that ſubject of <hi>Gods dwelling in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62274:15"/>good men,</hi> I take to be another excellent good Sermon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of Aſſuranee and praying by the Spirit (the ſubject of his fifth Chapter) with indifferency whether it be by a Form, or conceived Prayer.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Come to his fifth Chapter, which is to ſhew us what effects we are <hi>not</hi> to expect from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, having ſhewn before what effects (as he reckons them) are promiſed by it. And there are three <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended gifts</hi> (he ſaies) which are none of theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and ſo may not be hoped or prayed for upon that account. <hi>Immediate Revelation of the ſenſe of any Scripture; Abſolute aſſurance of our particular election; and the dictates of Extempore prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are three things belike he deſignes to have a ſling at, which he may do, but I muſt tell him in the way (whether any thing of this kind may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the holy Spirit or not) I am not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his argument, or the way of his bringing it about, that the effects for which we are to pray to God to give us his Spirit, are only things needful, and therefore we may not expect his help in extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary prayer, and theſe two other matters. This indeed may be argued from the Parables in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, that the gift it ſelf of the Spirit is a thing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. A gift which next to Gods giving his Son is the greateſt and moſt neceſſary to mankind; for as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62274:15"/>Chriſt was given for our <hi>Redemption,</hi> the Spirit is, and muſt be given for the <hi>Application.</hi> But that the effects of the Spirit being given ſhould be confined by him to theſe only he mentions, or ſuch only as he can fetch Scripture for (unleſs he could bring Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture alſo to ſay there are no more), is ſuch reaſoning as before a year is gone over his head, may give him occaſion to believe that ſome things may ſeem ſtrong in a Sermon, that are not fit for a Book that muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo a diſcuſſion.</p>
               <p>I do not think he hath ſpoken this as a <hi>cloſe Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Divine,</hi> nor yet that he hath laid down the method of thoſe benefits which we have from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, as a <hi>Comprehenſive Preacher:</hi> For when the Holy Ghoſt is not only our <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> but <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,</hi> and promiſed and ſent to the Church as <hi>the Comforter,</hi> it is ſtrange that the <hi>Conſolations of the Spirit</hi> ſhould be left out in the draught of thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which we are to expect from him. And when the Spirit is firſt given to a man to <hi>unite</hi> him to Chriſt, and this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is the primary effect of his having it, and by means hereof, all ſaving influences from the <hi>Head</hi> is derived: this by another would not have been forgotten.</p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt is given (I count) for our <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier,</hi> our <hi>Comforter,</hi> and our <hi>Guide.</hi> Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be comprehended in Sanctification, as the beginning of it, and Union is ſuppoſed to both. I cannot ſerve God without his grace, I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have the Spirit to <hi>Sanctifie</hi> me. If I ſerve him, I muſt be ſupported in his ſervice, I muſt therefore have him to <hi>Comfort</hi> me. When I am ſupported in my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62274:16"/>duty, I know not what uncertainties may befal me in all my ſpiritual and temporal concernments in this life, and therefore I muſt have him to <hi>Conduct</hi> me, and <hi>lead</hi> me in all my affairs, ſo as they may work together for the beſt, which he hath promiſed to thoſe that <hi>love him.</hi> Under this head now of the Spirits heavenly <hi>Guidance,</hi> are all thoſe things that are <hi>good</hi> for us, and not abſolutely <hi>neceſſary,</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; ſeeing <hi>we know not what to pray for as we ought</hi> (as we ſhall have occaſion farther to ſpeak of that Text by and by) <hi>but the Spirit helpeth us,</hi> that is, we know not in many things (<hi>temporal,</hi> ſays this Author, and I will ſay in <hi>ſpirituals</hi> too) what is beſt for us: and it is the Spirit that is our <hi>Guide</hi> as to theſe things, and <hi>Interceſſor</hi> for them: ſo that, be it the true Senſe of a place of Scripture, or Aſſurance, or aſſiſtance of us in our Prayers, or any thing elſe that we would have, we are, under the ſafe conduct of his word, and unperceptible motions, and with the reſignation of our wills unto him, (as our great diſpoſer for all good), to ſet our ſelves to our duty, and leave the iſſue to him. I will add, it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that this man never wrote this Book, than that in the promiſe of God's giving his Spirit to us, we ſhould be diſcouraged from praying to him, and truſting in him, for our direction in all the concerns of our ſouls, and outward conditions; who is the Comforter of the afflicted, the Sanctifier of all the faithful, and <hi>our Guide unto death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To his three things now in order.</p>
               <p>For the firſt of them, it is manifeſt, that in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times one of the miraculous gifts then given,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62274:16"/>was the gift of <hi>Interpretation;</hi> and there is no body that I know does pretend to any of theſe wonderful gifts in our days. I am ſure this Author cannot charge any thing of this kind upon Doctor <hi>Owen,</hi> who is a perſon of that induſtry and learning, as his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in this gift is well known to come another way. As for theſe arguments then, that the thing is not <hi>needful;</hi> and if <hi>profitable,</hi> that it is <hi>more profitable</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and to <hi>others,</hi> to get the ſenſe of any Scripture by enquiry and ſtudy, than by immediate Revelation (which if we could have it ſo, is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly falſe, as that <hi>Gold</hi> is not ſo good as <hi>Braſss</hi>) they may be ſpared, ſeeing there need no proof of this, that we are now to expect no Miracles from the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, there are two points about Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which this Author does confound; The one is, the aſſurance that a man is in a ſtate of Grace; and the other, an aſſurance of Salvation. That a man who is in a ſtate of Grace can never fall away ſinally and periſh (which is the Doctrine of Perſeverance), is a point of the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> againſt the Arminians and Lutherans. Whether a man may be aſſured that he is in a ſtate of Grace or no, is a Point between Proteſtants and Papiſts? For the former, Perſeverance depends on ſpecial Grace, and that on perſonal Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and I perceive this Gentleman hangs his head at that: but as for the latter, we may be in doubt what indeed his mind is. One would think by his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments at the beginning againſt Aſſurance, he ſhould be no Proteſtant, but he is; for we have his expreſs words for it, <hi>If we be the Children of God, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62274:17"/>poſſible for us to be aſſured of it.</hi> I muſt ask him then, is Aſſurance a good thing? St <hi>Paul</hi> had it, and St. <hi>John</hi> had it, <hi>Hereby we know we are paſſed from death to life,</hi>—and, <hi>By this we know, that we know him</hi>—If it be a thing then that is good, it muſt be an effect of God's Spirit: and this is proved, <hi>The Spirit alſo beareth witneſs with our ſpirits</hi>—This witneſs is our Aſſurance, and conſequently it may be prayed for according to the promiſe in <hi>Luke,</hi> as well as any other of the <hi>profitable</hi> effects he hath menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. Whether it be a thing <hi>needful,</hi> is a queſtion not needful, ſo long as it is <hi>good.</hi> It is an <hi>Egg,</hi> I hope, to argue with him, though it be not <hi>Bread.</hi> The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difficulty here is, to ſtate this Aſſurance. It is a controverſal point, and his one term <hi>Abſolute</hi> will do little to the deciſion. When our firſt Divines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Faith by a <hi>Perſuaſion of ſpecial mercy,</hi> ſo that without this aſſurance, they muſt think a man could not be ſaved, this was the moſt dangerous extreme on one hand: and that no man at all without Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (according to the <hi>Trent</hi> Doctors) can be aſſured that he is in God's favour, is the extreme on the other. But for the ſtating this aſſurance aright, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Proteſtant and Papiſt, To be a <hi>certainty</hi> not of <hi>Faith,</hi> becauſe the Scripture gives no teſtimony to any particular perſon, but a certainty <hi>moral</hi> (or of <hi>hope</hi>), which muſt be ſuch as excludes <hi>doubting,</hi> that is, all ſinful doubting, though not <hi>fear,</hi> or all fear that is, the <hi>fear of diffidence</hi> or diſtruſt, but not the <hi>fear of pious ſolicitude,</hi> is a work requires from me more deliberation, and more paper. This I will ſay only, that there is a <hi>neutral truth</hi> in the moſt of theſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62274:17"/>Controverſies that muſt be found out, in regard both to <hi>Practiſe</hi> as well as <hi>Theory,</hi> or we ſhall neither have our <hi>Conſciences</hi> nor <hi>Judgments</hi> well pacified in theſe matters.</p>
               <p>For the third thing then I will take a little more room; for, as I have had, and took an occaſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſpeak of Preaching by the Spirit, or with the <hi>demonſtration of it;</hi> ſo I think it alſo ſeaſonable; ſutable, and profitable to ſpeak of praying by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, unto which this Author himſelf, and much more the <hi>Friendly Debater,</hi> hath given ſuch ample <hi>opportunity,</hi> I wiſh I might not call it, in regard to man) good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Chriſtians, <hi>provocation.</hi> There is one Text there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in regard to this matter, as there was one in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the other, that requires our more ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. It is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26, 27. <hi>Likewiſe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit alſo helpeth our infirmities, for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought: but the Spirit it ſelf maketh interceſſion for us, with groanings which cannot be uttered. And he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, becauſe be maketh interceſſion for the Saints, according to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaking in the eighteenth Verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text, and in the twenty eight after it, about the afflictions of this life, which God's Children en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, whereby they are conformed to Chriſt in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, as they ſhall be in glory, this ingenious Author does apprehend that the expoſition of theſe words is to be confined to that matter altogether. <hi>We know not what to pray for as we ought.</hi> That is, we know not what is beſt for us in this mortal life, in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62274:18"/>regard to theſe troubles, perſecutions, or miſeries, whereby God intends ſometimes to do us much good; and we are therefore to ſeek to him with ſubmiſſion to his will in theſe things; having this encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our hearts, that the Spirit of God is our <hi>Guide</hi> (as I ſaid before, where this Author left it out) to direct us under all theſe Providences, and to be our <hi>Interceſſor</hi> alſo to obtain for us that which is like to prove beſt. He knows what that is, and ſtirs up in our ſouls many earneſt deſires after it; which, ſeeing we cannot reach our ſelves, theſe deſires can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be uttered by us; that is, are <hi>unutterable</hi> on that account; but ſo long as our requeſts are put up by him in thoſe deſires, God, who <hi>knows the mind of his own Spirit,</hi> hears theſe petitions, and grants thoſe very things which are beſt; that is, which <hi>he means:</hi> ſo that theſe things do, and ſhall certainly work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our good, as the Apoſtle ſays in the place, ſo long as we <hi>love</hi> him,</p>
               <p>This is in length the contents of that interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (and I ſuppoſe, according to his mind) which he hath ſedulouſly propoſed, both with authority and dexterity enough, if he were but as tender withal of preſerving that ſupport and warrantable expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Holy Spirit, which we have ground to take up in this place. I like well, of all that is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in regard to afflictions, unto the illuſtration of which ſenſe the Apoſtles own example (in his praying himſelf to have his troubles, the <hi>thorn in the fleſh,</hi> removed, and God's ſeeing it beſt for him, rather to afford him his <hi>ſufficient Grace</hi>) does opportunely conduce: but I do not approve by no means the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62274:18"/>down the interpretation of theſe words to that matter only. And much leſs will I give way to Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Hammond</hi>'s tranſlating the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Miſery:</hi> for ſeeing there is twenty places perhaps where the word is taken in this ſenſe, <hi>Infirmity,</hi> to one where it is taken in the other for <hi>Affliction;</hi> I muſt hold it but right to give it here (according to our Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Engliſh and Latin) its ordinary and genuine ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification.</p>
               <p>There is a great deal of comfort in theſe dear words of the Text, that <hi>the Spirit helps our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</hi> We are ſenſible with how many of them we are encompaſſed, not in regard to the thiugs without us, ſo much as within us: and if the weakneſſes, frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhortneſſes, imperfections, of our natures, perſons, abilities, tempers, conditions, be not provided for by the Divine ſuccor, we are undone. I look upon the man that will go to take away from me the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of theſe words, and this place, in regard to my addreſſes unto God, as him that is coming to pick my Lock, and take away my Treaſure. I will not ſuffer this man to rob me of my truſt, in the conduct and aſſiſtance of God's gracious good Spirit, in the very making and pouring out my Prayers for all the good that he and Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> can do me with both their Books. I do hate to put the name of <hi>Formal</hi> men, or <hi>Formaliſts</hi> on any party; yet ſeeing ſome of all parties are ſuch, I cannot but declare that man to be a <hi>Formaliſt</hi> to me, who ſhall offer to ſpeak the leaſt thing wilfully to damp the prayers of any the humbleſt ones, or weakeſt ones, in whom the Spirit of God does dwell.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62274:19"/>
               <p>There is another interpretation then of theſe words, and of the matter intended in them, that will carry it, I think from the former. The word <hi>Likewiſe</hi> which uſhers in the Text will carry it. When I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Context, the words in Verſe 28. following the Text does almoſt perſuade me that the matter this Author hath propoſed, may be intended; and I am pleaſed that it is likely; but the word <hi>Likewiſe</hi> doth import plainly, that the matter intended muſt relate to the words before, and not to thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and they carry it (I ſay) otherwiſe. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle therefore in this Chapter ſpeaking of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and thinking preſently of the evils they endure, does, for our ſupport upon that account, fall to tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us of the freedom we ſhall have in another ſtate; in compariſon whereof, theſe things deſerve not <hi>any reckoning.</hi> This is in Verſe 11. Of this ſtate then in the verſes following he treats, as that which is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of all the <hi>Creatures,</hi> and by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> a ſtate of liberty and glory, which we hope for, though we <hi>ſee</hi> it <hi>not,</hi> and with <hi>patience wait for it,</hi> in the Verſes imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately foregoing. And then in this Text it follows, that likewiſe we alſo through the Spirit pray for it. <hi>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities:</hi> Mark it, <hi>likewiſe,</hi> and <hi>alſo.</hi> This muſt hold the ſame matter together in this, and the former Verſes. <hi>For we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought.</hi> What is that then, but we are not able in this life to comprehend any thing to purpoſe of that ſtate of glorious liberty whereof he was ſpeaking. <hi>We know not what we ſhall be,</hi> ſays St. <hi>John, but we ſhall be like him.</hi> Things there be that are <hi>prepared</hi> for us,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62274:19"/>but what they are, neither hath the <hi>eye ſeen,</hi> nor <hi>ear heard,</hi> nor can the <hi>heart conceive</hi> truly of theſe things, which yet we <hi>hope</hi> for, and ſo <hi>pray</hi> for, the Spirit exciting theſe deſires in us who knows them, &amp; makes <hi>interceſſion</hi> by theſe <hi>groans</hi> or deſires which are <hi>unutterable,</hi> both in regard to our ſelves in that we know not the things of Heaven, and cannot utter them; and in regard to the nature of the things which are expreſly called by the Apoſtle when he was ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in his Spirit up thither to ſee them, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>things not poſſible to be uttered:</hi> And yet are they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us, though above our comprehenſion; and God who does <hi>above what we are able to ask or think,</hi> and knows what is the <hi>mind of his own Spirit,</hi> will grant them; becauſe this <hi>Interceſſion</hi> is by his <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment,</hi> and we are to ſupport our hearts, that this time is coming, when not only all theſe miſeries ſhall have an end, but we ſhall ſee Gods <hi>end</hi> in them all, in making them work for us, <hi>a far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weight of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are two interpretations then which I leave to the Reader; and he perhaps may chooſe neither of them: but in both of them that objection which is obvious from the Lord's Prayer is prevented. Chriſt hath taught us what we are to pray for, and yet does the Text tell us that we know not <hi>what we ſhould pray for as we ought.</hi> There are things in the Lord's Prayer which we are to pray for, and know that we ought to pray for them, and do pray for them; yet do we know them but <hi>in part;</hi> and we are more ſhort in our knowing how to pray for them, as <hi>beſt</hi> for us. When we pray for <hi>deliverance from evil,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62274:20"/>
                  <hi>temptation,</hi> that includes our preſent troubles; and theſe are the things <hi>we know not,</hi> according to the <hi>firſt</hi> Interpretation. When we pray that God's <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may come,</hi> that includes the things of heaven; and theſe are the things <hi>we know not,</hi> according to the <hi>ſecond</hi> Interpretation. That which cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in regard to theſe two Petitions, muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in all others under a like condition. There is little reaſon for this Author then to pick a quarrel with Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> for attributing too much to the aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, in the making our Prayers (who is ſo very cautious to allow any thing but in regard to the <hi>matter</hi> of them) when there is ſo much more included here in the Spirits praying for us, and that for the things <hi>we know not;</hi> as it may make any man at a ſtand who goes about to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Holy One almoſt at all, for fear of preſuming on the <hi>Ark</hi> of his imperceptible operations.</p>
               <p>Having ſaid this, I have but three or four notes more upon this Text, which muſt not be waved. It is to be conſidered firſt, we have the Spirit put here into the Office of Interceſſor, and there is a practical caſe requires ſatisfaction. Chriſt hath promiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again, that <hi>whatſoever we ask by Faith in his name, according to his will, we ſhall have it.</hi> There is many a good man now troubled at this, that he hath prayed often, and not been heard. It muſt be anſwered therefore upon this account, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever requeſt we make, or any one makes, with the qualifications expreſt, it is, and muſt be put up to God by the Holy Spirit; and though it be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered according to <hi>our mind,</hi> it is according to <hi>his,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62274:20"/>who maketh interceſſion for us. A ſecond note is this, that though the Apoſtle be ſuppoſed to bring in theſe words, [<hi>We know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought</hi>] with regard to the Context, it will not follow from the <hi>inſtance</hi> of one or other of theſe <hi>particular</hi> matters to be <hi>intended,</hi> that all others muſt be <hi>excluded;</hi> but rather, that the <hi>univerſal</hi> matters of Prayer, ſo far as they are ſubject to the like condition, muſt be certainly alſo <hi>concluded.</hi> Note in the third place, that though there does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſome reaſon from the objection mentioned, for limiting theſe words, [<hi>We know not what to pray for</hi>] there is no reaſon for limitation of the firſt part of the Text [<hi>The Spirit helpeth our infirmities.</hi>] For when it is affirmed that it is by reaſon of our infirmity that we know not what to pray for, it does not follow that therefore that is <hi>all</hi> our infirmity. We have many more infirmities to be helpt than this, in making our Prayers. Note in the laſt place, that though the <hi>groans unutterable</hi> in the Text be expounded in both theſe interpretations, with regard to the <hi>matter prayed for,</hi> they may very likely be better expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with regard to theſe <hi>infirmities,</hi> to be <hi>helped:</hi> that is, though we are ſuch (many of us) as are ſo weak that we cannot utter our requeſts, or frame our deſires into petitions; yet by the Spirit we are aſſiſted ſome way, to put theſe ſmall <hi>unutterable groans</hi> with his <hi>good motions</hi> together, ſo as they are <hi>accepted</hi> in Heaven, It is not by reaſon of the intenſiveneſs or <hi>greatneſs,</hi> but becauſe of their <hi>ſmallneſs</hi> (ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Perkins</hi>) that theſe <hi>groans</hi> are <hi>unutterable.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62274:21"/>
               <p>I do not think therefore that it is in this Authors power to divert that favour which this Text does caſt upon thoſe Prayers which he calls <hi>ex tempore,</hi> the Ancients <hi>ex pectore;</hi> feeing ſuch Prayers do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, or ſlow moſt genuinely from the motions that are upon the ſoul; and which, ſo long as they are good, we are to aſcribe to the Holy Spirit. And when this is granted on all hands, that he does <hi>excite our affections,</hi> who is there can ſay, what influence, or how much, that work alone hath, or muſt have, on our <hi>expreſſions? The Holy Spirit being intimate to our ſouls, can affect us when we are not ſenſible of it, and produce effects upon our minds in that manner as if they were meerly the effects of our own reaſoning,</hi> ſays this very Author. And why then do ſuch able and <hi>good men</hi> (for ſuch I hope they indeed are, and that they do not ſpeak what they do, as <hi>Scoffers</hi>) let ſuch <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> and <hi>Debates</hi> as theſe come from them which carry a tendency in them to repreſs that devotion, that has in it, or pretends at leaſt, the moſt of warmth and enlargement of affection in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as if a <hi>coldneſs</hi> or <hi>beadiſhneſs</hi> in the performance was to be preferred as more ſafe and wiſe, when Chriſt that hath taught us to <hi>pray,</hi> does alſo exhort us to <hi>fervency</hi> and <hi>importunity?</hi> I cannot tell what they would have by it, unleſs it be that all ſhould come in to the Liturgy, or elſe they ſhould have no other Prayers. But this is more than can be expected in conſcience. The circumſtances of praying <hi>in a Book,</hi> or <hi>without,</hi> is not ſo material as that they ſhould be ſo earneſt. I am a profeſt Neuter againſt extremes, and will apply that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>If we be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62274:21"/>beſides our ſelves, it is to Godward; and if we be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, it is for your cauſe.</hi> And ſo having got over this one Text, I will now preſent you my poor thoughts more cloſely on this ſubject, with reference to <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical</hi> and <hi>Extempore</hi> Devotion.</p>
               <p>There are four things here therefore to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and preſented. The Spirit of Prayer. The Gift of Prayer. Praying in the Spirit. Praying by it, or with it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spirit of Prayer</hi> I apprehend to be no other than the Spirit of Grace or Regeneration, with the <hi>connotation</hi> of its operation on the ſoul, in regard to this duty. There is no Chriſtian born of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, whereby he cries <hi>Abba Father;</hi> as no man born after the fleſh without his breathing. There is no holy thought, meditation, deſire after God, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt that is acceptable to him in Chriſt, but it is from this Spirit of Adoption or Prayer. It follows then, that foraſmuch as any gracious and regenerate man may uſe a <hi>Form</hi> if he pleaſes, and ſome ſuch have uſed a Form ſometimes as well as <hi>Conceived Prayer,</hi> that it is a conceit exceedingly extravagant, and in no wiſe to be approved, to think that a Liturgy or uſe of a Form is inconſiſtent with the <hi>Spirit of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> Suppoſe we ſaw thoſe holy men, <hi>Bradford, Rogers, Philpot, Saunders,</hi> ſaying their Prayers out of the Pſalter, and bleſſing God for the Book of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. I will pour upon the houſe of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>the Spirit of Prayer and Supplication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Gift of Prayer</hi> I account to be a natural or acquired, not infuſed ability or faculty of expreſſing the thoughts and affections with fluency or readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62274:22"/>in Prayer. It does depend chiefly I think upon an aptneſs of memory, retaining the ſentences and very words of Scripture, when others can retain the ſenſe only; together with a warm fancy, and a tongue that is voluble. In ſhort, it is a ready utterance, which muſt be always diſtinguiſhed from the former. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a perſon, who was otherwiſe of large parts, filled with all preſent matter for adminiſtring a word in ſeaſon to the weary, who in praying ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with me, I have obſerved to hum and hack ſo in his Prayer, that I never heard any ſo unable to expreſs himſelf in my life, who yet would uſe only concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Prayer; and in the mean while I have been ſo aſſured of the Grace of God, and eminency of that Grace in the perſon, of that ſincerity in his duty, ſuch an humbling under ſin, fervency in his petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, melting under the ſence of God's mercy and pardon; and in a word, a heart it ſelf no leſs broken than thoſe words, that I cannot but be ſatisfied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond doubt, for ever ſince, that the <hi>Gift of Prayer</hi> is one thing, and the <hi>Spirit of Prayer</hi> is another.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as the gifts which are adminiſtred to men by God's Spirit, are beſtowed for uſe, and the edification of the Church, if a Liturgy or form of Prayer were impoſed on the Clergy in oppoſition to that proviſion which God hath made and appointed for the good of his Church, that is, <hi>Gifts unto men for the work of the Miniſtry,</hi> or if the Biſhops would not ſuffer them to be employed to the end they are given, I do not know any argument of ſo much weight, and like to be prevailing with Religious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt Common-Prayer as this allegation, <hi>As
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62274:22"/>every one hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Grace of God.</hi> But we muſt not judge ſo of our Superiors. The Churches impoſing a Liturgy, and ſet forms on the Miniſter is to be lookt on as <hi>cumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> to his gifts, and not as <hi>deſtructive</hi> to them. There is the gift of Prayer, as of Prudence and Knowledge to Miniſters, as they are <hi>ſingle,</hi> and as they are in <hi>conjunction.</hi> Theſe forms of Prayer are the exerciſe of the mutual gifts of the Churches Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in conjunction; and when this <hi>Common Service</hi> of theirs is performed in the <hi>Pew,</hi> the Miniſter is leſt to the uſe of his ſingle gifts in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> without any prejudicing the one by the other. Indeed, if the Common-Prayer be made a Napkin to wrap up the Talents of any, I will not juſtifie the abuſe of that, which hath its uſe and commendation upon other reaſons. And yet by the way, I do not know more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, whether all thoſe Texts which ſpeak of gifts for the Church, and which argue power thereupon to <hi>profit with them,</hi> are not to be underſtood of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in thoſe times; ſo that when it was manifeſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the Holy Ghoſt himſelf <hi>then,</hi> to forbid the uſe of thoſe Gifts to any, which he had miniſtred to them to that end: it may not be ſo altogether, as to thoſe natural gifts and talents that men have <hi>now;</hi> which notwithſtanding they are not to be denied to be alſo from the Spirit, (ſeeing even <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and his fellows skill in working in curious works, is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, and every good gift is ſaid to be of God). I queſtion whether the perſon himſelf be either ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to put them to that <hi>particular</hi> uſe, having
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62274:23"/>them from nature to <hi>general</hi> ſervice, or that there does appear the like injury to God and the Church, in ſome reſtraint on <hi>them,</hi> as there would be in the <hi>other.</hi> There are <hi>diverſity of Gifts, but the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Praying <hi>in the Spirit</hi> I apprehend to be praying with thoſe qualifications which are wrought in us by the Spirit, and preſcribed by him in the word, to make our Prayers acceptable to God. Praying in the Spirit (ſay Practical Divines) conſiſts not in a copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of words, but extent of affections. The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating of all does lie in the operation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on our hearts in this duty. We muſt pray alſo <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's will,</hi> which is another qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Prayer: and when a man does pray according to what the Spirit hath directed in the Word, he may be ſaid very appoſitely to pray <hi>in the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two things there are then more particularly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I will place this operation. The one is, the Spirit doth many times pitch the heart upon thoſe objects or things which are moſt fit for us to ask. The other is and then doth excite our deſires, and enlarge our affections about the ſame. <hi>The Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities, for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf maketh interceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</hi> I will not doubt to quote this Text again for thus much. It is ſaid that Satan entred into <hi>Judas</hi> when he went to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his Lord. And Satan moved <hi>David</hi> to number the people. It appears from hence, that Satan puts evil thoughts in the heart, and pitches them on ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects he tempts them withal. The Spirit of God
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62274:23"/>doubtleſs does no leſs in the good actions which he ſtirs up in Gods Saints, <hi>He puts good thoughts in the mind, and repreſents things to us</hi> (ſays the Author of the <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> himſelf) <hi>more clearly than we could make them by all our reaſoning.</hi> I might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps cite ſomething from this Gentleman to ſute with this, but I think the ſubject here too grave, to make him my Authority. When the Spirit is ſaid to help us (in the Text before exagitated) to make our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers even about things our ſelves <hi>know not,</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for us therein according to the <hi>will of God,</hi> it cannot be imagined but thus much muſt be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that operation, whatſoever farther he does for us. Now then when the Spirit doth not only move the affections in relation to the things the heart is upon in thoſe groanings mentioned to be <hi>unutterable,</hi> but pitches the heart upon theſe things, thoſe very things or objects themſelves (ſometimes at leaſt) that are <hi>moſt ſutable to our wants,</hi> which he knows <hi>better than we:</hi> and <hi>moſt agreeable to God's will,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we regard his <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>word,</hi> or the will of his <hi>providence,</hi> and what he is minded to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh for us, wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he alone <hi>does know, and not we:</hi> it does ſeem that the preſcribing a ſet form to our prayers does indeed put ſome ſtint to one part of this operation (I ſay i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> really ſeems ſo), which is the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting good thoughts, or the good things themſelves into our minds, or pitching our hearts upon the things he knows beſt for every one when the Miniſter does not know it: though it puts no ſtint to him in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration on the affections, exciting or enlarging them after thoſe objects, or the petitions which the Church
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62274:24"/>hath preſcribed. And how far this will go for the preferring of <hi>Conceived Prayer</hi> before a <hi>Form</hi> I leave to that learned and able Doctor of the Church, and this ingenious perſon who is following him, to give judgment.</p>
               <p>There are many reaſons in regard to the Miniſter, if he hath no Gift, or if he have, and have not grace, leaſt he be puffed up in the oſtentation of it, and of the Congregation under ſome conſiderations, why a ſet form is more eligible, when in regard of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly godly, who are endowed with the Giſt and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit both: there is this reaſon from <hi>praying in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> to be alledged for <hi>conceived prayer</hi> (I muſt ſay, in the Pulpit) out of that Doctors own words before named, as nothing for ought I know, can be put in ballance againſt it; for notwithſtanding the ſeverity of ſome reflections he hath upon ſuch as are of that mind and practiſe, I do not ſee any reaſon at all why a fluent expreſſion, a raiſed voice, a zeal in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, a melting ſoul touching phraſe out of Scripture, with newneſs and variety of the ſame, and the like circumſtances, which many times pierce the heart that is ſlat otherwiſe, and hath <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all we can to quicken it, ſhould any way be derogatory to the ſound and wholeſome requeſts otherwiſe which a man puts up to God in his prayer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if ſuch circumſtances indeed as theſe which will raiſe the affections are incident to <hi>conceived Prayer,</hi> which are not to a <hi>ſet form,</hi> then hath that worthy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor adminiſtred an effectual reaſon why the very ſame material petitions or confeſſions of a Prayer are better oftentimes when delivered <hi>extempore</hi> than in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62274:24"/>
                  <hi>form,</hi> and conſequently an argument for <hi>one</hi> above the <hi>other,</hi> even while he is ſeeking occaſion hereby to blaſt conceived Prayer. And why indeed (let me ask) ſhould not the Church be as ready to uſe thoſe Gifts which God hath given unto any, to excite the people the more in their Devotions, as well as they are to make uſe of Organs, and diverſity of Voices in their chooſing Singing-men and Singing-boyes to that purpoſe? The ſame Pſalm in an Anthem hath another operation on the heart of a devout Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt out of the mouth of a <hi>Choire,</hi> than it hath in a private <hi>Parlour.</hi> And if a Non-conformiſt does find the like experience as to an <hi>Extempore</hi> Prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any <hi>Compoſure,</hi> why ſhould that Doctor, or this perſon be any leſs pleaſed with it? The uſe of a man's <hi>Gifts</hi> in prayer is but an <hi>Organ of God's ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> a warbling, and holy deſcant upon the plain requeſts of the heart, to affect it the more with them: and an <hi>Organ</hi> is the uſe of thoſe <hi>Gifts,</hi> as I may ſay, which are of <hi>man's making,</hi> or which man hath <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Church,</hi> for the ſame end, to wit, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livening our dull affections, while we are meditating, praying, and praiſing the Almighty.</p>
               <p>To return, we know that Chriſt bids his Diſciples, when they were brought before Magiſtrates, they ſhould leave it to the Spirit to direct them what they ſhould ſpeak, without ſolicitude for matter or words. It is a modeſt rule when any thing extraordinary is promiſed to the Church, that it is to be expected at firſt; but afterward we are to look only for what is ordinary. I believe that ſuch aſſiſtance as that but in an ordinary way and manner is always to be expected
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62274:25"/>by the godly with faith in all they are put upon for his glory: and upon ſuppoſition of the Spirits ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting ſometimes the very objects into the Miniſters mind (in ſuch a way as is agreeable to ſpiritual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration though we are ignorant how) which he knowes does befit the preſent frame of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, How much more likely is the performance of the duty after theſe motions, when there is a gift in the Miniſter to follow them, to affect the hearts of all preſent, then the performance of it after a <hi>form</hi> of man, whether of anothers, or his own compoſure.</p>
               <p>This I muſt ſay with faithfulneſs (who am not for the ruſt of any Miniſters parts, ſeeing he hath ſuch continual occaſion to uſe them), yet not without theſe two or three cautions. The one is that in the prayers which the Church hath compoſed we may humbly conceive that the Spirit of God did pitch the hearts of thoſe who were to joyn in their gifts (or judgements) for the compoſure, upon thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or matter which is moſt agreeable to our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Congregations, as it does the heart of any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Miniſter upon thoſe things as is moſt <hi>agreeable to his will</hi> for the preſent occaſion. Another is, that if a Miniſter hath not the gift to expreſs himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtudy, and does therefore take pains for his prayer as for his Preaching, having a gift perhaps up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his pains and ſtudy (though none elſe) that does equal, if not excel his that hath the beſt without it, he may expect the ſame aſſiſtance on his ſtudy, that the Spirit ſhould help his infirmities as to the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his mind thoſe things which are moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive for his people to receive, and moſt agreeable to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62274:25"/>his will to give, as any other may, who hath the readieſt gift to follow his preſent motions. The laſt is, that though a Miniſter therefore ſhould take heed of drying up his gifts by one conſtant form in the Pulpit where he hath liberty; yet if any do ſo I do hold that it is not a ſufficient ground for his people to run from him into ſeparation; for though that will make his Miniſtry the leſs comfortable, as the Miniſtry of one who hath leſs gifts muſt be leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable than one that hath greater, yet the <hi>majus</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> does not vary the ſpecies, and this reaches not to make the ſervice unlawful. Beſides, he who prayes with the largeſt gifts of prayer does but offer a ſtinted form (which is ſaid commonly) as to the hearers particular ſtate, and the ſtinting of the <hi>Object</hi> does not yet ſtint the Spirit however in his operation on the <hi>affections. Praying alwaies with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of prayer and ſupplications in the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Praying <hi>with the Spirit,</hi> or by it, in the laſt place is that we find in the dayes of the Apoſtles when they had extraordinary adminiſtrations of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in gifts that were miraculous, inſomuch that they ſpake with tongues and ſo preached and prayed. Thoſe that ſpake (I apprehend) underſtood not themſelves what they delivered, but every one in whoſe tongue they ſpake were edified, and therefore we read of ſome that did interpret. Thoſe were ſuch it is like as had skill in more tongues than their own, or elſe in caſe there were none ſuch, the fame miraculous power might enable ſome for the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation as others to ſpeak. Thus praying <hi>with the Spirit</hi> is oppoſed to praying <hi>with the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62274:26"/>and the Apoſtle prefers praying with the underſtanding before it. There is no perſon had cauſe therefore to brag of this, if he had it; and there is none of any ſect among us that pretend to it. And ſo I think (having ſaid what I intended otherwiſe), that neither the Gentleman, nor I, need to be put to any more words about it. <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the cloſer judgement of the Author (in his ſixth Chapter) which is Arminian; and of Election, Free-will, and Grace, upon account of his opinion; Of the ſalvability of Heathen, and other incidental matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Deſcend to his ſixth Chapter, which is to ſhew us, <hi>who thoſe are</hi> to whom the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> and <hi>given.</hi> Theſe perſons are <hi>Believers,</hi> who yet are not <hi>holy perſous.</hi> This is his Notion. They cannot be holy till they have the Spirit to ſanctifie them, and yet they muſt believe and pray becauſe that is the condition upon which the Spirit is given. The holy Spirit conſequently and his ſpecial grace is neceſſary to <hi>Good works</hi> or ſanctification: but <hi>Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> is antecedent to it, or muſt be in a mans power, before it.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs I am made ſenſible of the ſagacity of this Author upon my reading this Chapter, which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62274:26"/>I did not heed ſo much before, and I perceive which way his mind is hankering. It was this very light which carried St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſo much in his firſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. The doctrine of <hi>Pelagius</hi> at the firſt broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, conſiſted mainly in this point, that God did give his grace according to mens merits. This doctrine ſeemed to the Father too arrogant for man, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory to God. That the grace of God and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life is given to ſome, and not to others, is manifeſt. That the reaſon muſt be in regard of ſomething that one man does and not another, ſeemed to him unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable. That good works ſhould be it, appears againſt the Scripture, <hi>not by works leſt any man ſhould boaſt.</hi> Beſides, if a man ſhould be allowed to be able to do any good works to merit Gods grace by the ſtrength of nature, what need were there of prayer for aid from God or the help of his Spirit? Man ſhould have need of <hi>induſtry</hi> here, not <hi>prayer.</hi> If not <hi>works</hi> then, what muſt it be but that which is ſo often contradiſtinguiſhed to works, and that is <hi>Faith?</hi> For the Scripture that ſaies <hi>not of Works but of Grace,</hi> does ſay likewiſe, <hi>It is of faith that it may be of Grace.</hi> Here then is that which muſt be in mans power. That a man could not do <hi>good works</hi> without grace St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> always aſſerted, for this was his meaning when he ſaies that <hi>good works do not preceed but follow juſtification,</hi> underſtanding by juſtifying, the making a man juſt by inherent grace, as the Schools do after him. But that a man can <hi>believe</hi> if he will by the uſe of his natural facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties only, is what he did maintain readily, thinking no body could deny it. According to this clear ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62274:27"/>prehenſion as he then took it up, he did proceed to his doctrine of Election, which being defined by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents before his time always <hi>ex praeſcientia,</hi> he now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines to be of this Faith foreſeen. It muſt not be <hi>ex operibus praeviſis,</hi> becauſe that will oppoſe grace, but <hi>ex praevifa fide,</hi> and that will ſalve all objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We are to conceive of other things to follow agreeably, as <hi>Arminius</hi> that acute and I think pious Divine hath ſince taken up the notion (when <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> himſelf retracted it) and upon his own ſtock improved it.</p>
               <p>It is me now (I muſt ſay) ſomething notable to ſee the ſeeds of the ſame light ſpringing up in this Gentleman as formerly actuared two ſuch ſearching Divines as <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Arminius</hi> were: and I cannot therefore without guilt of diſingenuity paſs over any thing which he hath offered for the farther cultivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. For doing this, I obſerve he enters firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an adventure to make ſome change of our terms in Divinity. The <hi>ſtate of nature,</hi> and a <hi>ſtate of Grace</hi> are terms that ſignifie <hi>Regeneration</hi> and <hi>Unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with all men, even in our practical Books: and he will have us by <hi>a ſtate of Nature</hi> to underſtand the <hi>state of a Heathen;</hi> and by a <hi>ſtate of Grace,</hi> the ſtate of every one under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> The Goſpel now bringing a man into this ſtate, <hi>a ſtate of Grace,</hi> he diſtinguiſhes of this Grace the Goſpel brings. And it is either that which <hi>goes before</hi> our Faith, or <hi>follows</hi> it. That which <hi>goes before</hi> he accounts it all <hi>Common Grace;</hi> that which is given <hi>after</hi> it, ſpecial <hi>Grace.</hi> Ordinarily, by the way, that grace which is given to the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Elect,</hi> we call <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62274:27"/>Grace,</hi> and that which is <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Elect</hi> we call <hi>ſpecial grace,</hi> whether <hi>before</hi> or <hi>after</hi> Faith. But he offers his reaſon. The Grace which the Goſpel brings, is either (ſays he) that which is given <hi>upon condition,</hi> or that which is given <hi>upon none.</hi> That which is conditional muſt be given only to ſome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſome only perform that condition, and that which is given but to ſome is <hi>ſpecial Grace.</hi> That which is given upon no condition, muſt be therefore (or rather may be) appropriated to all, and ſo is <hi>Common Grace.</hi> Thus he Theologizes, when we ordinarily do not account it <hi>common</hi> grace, becauſe <hi>every</hi> one has it; but becauſe the <hi>Reprobate</hi> as well as the <hi>Elect</hi> have it: and we do not call it <hi>ſpecial Grace</hi> only, becauſe <hi>ſome</hi> have it, but becauſe the <hi>Elect only</hi> have it: ſo that, that Grace which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but to ſome, if it be given to any Reprobate as well as the Elect, we call not <hi>ſpecial,</hi> but <hi>common</hi> Grace. Well, but theſe terms being premiſed, that Grace now which he calls <hi>ſpecial,</hi> the grace of the Goſpel, is promiſed on the <hi>condition of Faith.</hi> It is <hi>Faith</hi> is the firſt thing upon which all depends. If this be not in the power of every one, the terms of the Goſpel ſhall be unperformable. And that this Faith may be in our power, he will have a preventing Grace (which is not the Grace it ſelf of the Goſpel, that being all <hi>conditional,</hi> but ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine aſſiſtance accompanying it) as enables every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that hears the Goſpel to believe, unleſs they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reject it, He is afraid of Pelagianiſm, to allow that any do or can believe of their own ſtrength with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grace (though <hi>Auſtin</hi> when he entertained this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62274:28"/>mans thoughts, made no ſcruple of that) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will help out the good Father here very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the intimation of a Grace, that being not confined to any condition, muſt be common, and ſo belong to all who are brought into that ſtate, which is a <hi>ſtate of Grace,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> of being <hi>under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</hi> when Chriſt ſays, <hi>Go preach the Goſpel, he that believes not ſhall be damned.</hi> It is repugnant (he argues) to the goodneſs and juſtice of God, that he ſhould with-hold that aſſiſtance as is neceſſary to make this condition <hi>poſſible,</hi> and <hi>believing</hi> without ſuch Grace is <hi>impoſſible.</hi> Upon this Grace then, which all have, who have the word preached, a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>his</hi> Believer. This Faith or bare Chriſtianity with Prayer is the condition of that promiſe, that <hi>God will give his Holy Spirit to thoſe that ask him.</hi> The Spirit being given, we are to improve his Grace. This improvement is the condition of that farther promiſe, that <hi>God will dwell in us.</hi> That God will <hi>give us his Spirit,</hi> and that he will <hi>dwell in us,</hi> are the principal promiſes of Grace in the Goſpel, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with this Author, underſtanding Grace only of theſe operations. This implies a plentiful commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of farther degrees of Grace for perſeverance. Upon the condition of perſeverance we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>Lo here the notion of this worthy Author, wherein I think I have done him and my Reader right to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it with all the light about it, as I was able to draw it from him. I will now requite the ingenuity and liberty of his opinion, with the like freedom in my Animadverſions.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62274:28"/>
               <p>In the firſt place I do apprehend that theſe things have lien in the mind of this Gentleman, not yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years; and I think that a man had need to take no leſs time than <hi>Jacob</hi> ſerved for <hi>Rachel,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well before he <hi>wed</hi> himſelf to a <hi>Party</hi> in the controverſie of the <hi>Five points,</hi> eſpecially if he take to that ſide which ſtands condemned by the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> with our Britiſh Divines in it; who being ſent thither by Authority, were to determine nothing we may be ſure, but what was agreeable to the Doctrine of our Church; and alſo when the Father who firſt ſprang that notion which this Author is in queſt of, did upon moſt mature deliberation himſelf forſake it, and that only (as I believe) upon a full conviction from the Scripture, which led him into the Doctrine of Abſolute Election, which this man as ſuddenly rejects, as he maturely embraced, ſhewing himſelf even fond of it in all his latter Writings, even to the death. Which makes me add this moreover, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as I ſee ſeveral of our younger Divines, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of more quick parts, ſo forward upon theſe points, I will paſs my conjecture, that by that time they have well <hi>bred their teeth,</hi> they will not perhaps be ſo much <hi>in pain</hi> (as they ſeem now to be) to run into diſputation (as they do) either with <hi>Calvin,</hi> or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Owen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſecond place I cannot lightly give the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman my approbation to his new coin. I am ſenſible of ſo much hurt and ill conſequence that may come of this boldneſs to go about to alter terms that have gotten into our Divinity, when it is not that of the <hi>Schools</hi> only, but of our <hi>Sermons</hi> and practical Books,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62274:29"/>that this Author is not aware of what he does. It is the raw Divine will take up theſe terms, and when he comes to uſe them, he will be ſo confounded himſelf, and confound the people that hear him, that they will be as thoſe that ſpeak in a ſtrange tongue, one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. For inſtance, what if a green Preacher comes and tells his Congregation after this Author, that all that hear him are in a ſtate of Grace? What if he comes, and preaches on, that the Goſpel gives no ground for us to expect any ſpecial Grace till we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the condition of the Goſpel? How odd muſt this appear to the hearers in any judicious Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when we know the firſt Grace (we mean effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual) is given <hi>without condition?</hi> Yet let this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor explain theſe words for him; that by <hi>ſpecial Grace</hi> we muſt always underſtand Grace promiſed to <hi>qualified perſons;</hi> ſo that all he means muſt be, that that Grace which is promiſed on condition, is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till we perform the condition, the matter admits of no contradiction. Beſides this evil, the new for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of terms which are received to other ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Church, is methinks but like a man who hath ſome very curious work to engrave, and when he has all thoſe tools in his ſhop that are made on purpoſe for the doing that work, he will uſe his knife only. This may indeed commend the <hi>rarity</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry,</hi> but not the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of that workman, who could have done his buſineſs better, if he had uſed thoſe Inſtruments which were ready by him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for it.</p>
               <p>In the third place there is one thing I muſt needs obſerve, wherein I think this Gentleman in his Heto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62274:29"/>to be a little too Orthodox; and that is in his ordering the ſcheme of his notion ſo, as that the <hi>homo Evangelizatus</hi> only ſhall be the ſubject of God's Grace: that is, when he does hold forth a common Grace vouchſaſed to all who are under the Goſpel, enabling them to believe, if they will, upon which the promiſe of the Spirit belongs to them, and ſo the ſpecial Grace of it upon Goſpel conditions unto ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; he does leave all the world beſides in ſuch a ſtate, as is without all Grace, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a remedileſs condition. Whereas he may find in the Schools, that there is an univerſal Grace maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many, which they call <hi>ſufficient</hi> (and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is that which this Author means by his <hi>common</hi> Grace), as no man is without, whether Heathen or Chriſtian; in the improvement whereof, farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are attainable upon the <hi>Habenti dabitur,</hi> till it comes to be effectual; ſo that it ſhall lie upon the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the will in every body, whether they be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or damned. I know the Author may deſert theſe, and not be ſingular in this point of his opinion, ſo long as he hath the Fathers generally, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> more particularly, the Papiſt and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, with the eighteenth Article of our own on his ſide: and that which may pleaſe this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſomething more. I remember <hi>Arminius</hi> in ſome place of his works, does expreſly exclude all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens from ſalvation; though many that have tread in his ſteps otherwiſe, have been more kind to the Nations. I have ſome little light therefore here (or I believe it to be ſo) to offer to this very ſuſceptible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. There is a three-fold Government (in one, to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62274:30"/>ſpeak accurately) that God hath had in the world over man in reference to his chief end, the ſalvation of his ſoul. The firſt was by the Law of Nature, the ſecond, by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the third by the Law of Chriſt. Before God gave his Law unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the whole world was under that Law, which is <hi>written in the heart.</hi> God muſt govern man by that only, when there was no other. This Law now, <hi>writ in mans heart</hi> (we are to know) is two-fold; for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture coming under a double conſideration, as <hi>entire,</hi> and as <hi>fallen,</hi> the Law muſt be double; the Law of <hi>innocent</hi> nature (or <hi>Law of Innocency</hi>), and the Law of <hi>lapſed</hi> nature, which is the <hi>Law of Grace</hi> or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy toward man in regard to that condition. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it more fully, there is <hi>Lex Naturae</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>Lex connaturalis gratiae;</hi> The <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>connatural Law of Grace,</hi> as <hi>Suarez</hi> has it in his Book <hi>De Legibus.</hi> I am pleaſed much with the terms, though I found not that he did well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, or explain them himſelf. Only thus much he ſays, that the Ancients before <hi>Moſes,</hi> who were governed by the Law of Nature only, muſt have this <hi>Lex connaturalis gratiae</hi> together with it, or comprehended under it; or elſe no man then upon earth could be ſaved: which is a truth ſo evident, as makes the proof of that Law, by that reaſon alone, to be good. When he terms this Law then a Law <hi>connatural,</hi> I underſtand by it, that this Law of lapſed Nature, this Law of Grace, or remedying Law is written in the heart of man, in regard to his <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> nature, no leſs than the Law of <hi>pure</hi> nature it ſelf was. The Law of Nature, as I take it, is the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62274:30"/>dictates of right reaſon, declaring to us our duty to God, to our ſelves, and to our neighbours; and the light of the ſame reaſon will dictate to us, when we have failed in that duty, to repent and turn to God with truſting to his mercy and pardon if we do ſo, and not elſe. We do find it legible in our hearts that God is good and wiſely gratious to pity our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and conſider our loſt eſtate, and neceſſary frailty, as that there is a God, and any worſhip that is at all due to him. <hi>There is mercy with thee that thou ſhouldſt be feared.</hi> And theſe Characters thus engraven in the heart of man, is the ſame law of Grace in the practical contents, as is more largely paraphraſed upon, by the <hi>Prophets</hi> in the <hi>Old,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the <hi>New</hi>-Teſtament. There is no difference at all in the <hi>Subſtance</hi> (as Divines ſpeak) but in the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi> It is as one lately hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed it lively) no otherwiſe than as a Book thrice Printed; the ſecond Edition is larger than the firſt, and the third moſt compleat and perfect. This I will ſay, the Covenant was ſtill on foot; the Condition ſincerity according to their light; men were judged by it, and many ſaved. Here only is the difference, that the foundation on which all this is laid, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, Righteouſneſs and Sacrifice of Chriſt, comes not to be revealed but in Types, and darker promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, till the promulgation of the Goſpel. Now, I ſay, that though the Heathen be not under (or have not) this Law of Grace, in the third and laſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our, or in the ſtate under the Goſpel; yet they are under it (or have it) in the ſtate of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, or as they had it in the firſt promulgation;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62274:31"/>and upon ſuppoſition that any of them do according to the light they have, live up in ſincerity to this Law; I dare not be the man that ſhall deny but <hi>through the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (procuring this Law or Covenant for them, as for us, and all the world) <hi>they ſhall be ſaved even as we,</hi> and we ſhall be ſaved <hi>even as they.</hi> Not to leave this yet. I have learned from <hi>Cicero,</hi> that all Laws muſt be derived from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Reaſon and Will. I have learned from others, that this Reaſon of God in his Government of all things agreeably to his own nature and the nature of his Creatures is the <hi>Eternal Law.</hi> I have learned from the Scripture, that there is a <hi>Law of Works,</hi> and a <hi>Law of Grace.</hi> I do learn by conſequence that theſe Laws (as frames of Gods Government over man) muſt be reconcileable with the <hi>Eternal Law,</hi> or the reaſon of his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> the one of them being fit for the eſtate of man in <hi>Innocency,</hi> the other for his <hi>Lapſed</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How theſe Laws do now conſiſt, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with one another, while the Scripture ſaies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we are <hi>freed from the Law,</hi> and ſometimes that it is <hi>eſtabliſhed,</hi> That not a <hi>tittle of it ſhall paſs,</hi> and that we are <hi>not under the Law, but under Grace,</hi> I do not intend here any full deciſion. I will draw only one chief ſtroke towards it. The Law may be conſidered as the <hi>Rule of man's duty,</hi> or Meaſure of Good and Evil according to his own nature, and Gods: Or as the <hi>Inſtrument of God's Government</hi> over man, or Meaſure of his dealing with us, or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us, according to our diſcernings. It cannot be conceived but ſo long as the <hi>Nature</hi> of God and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62274:31"/>Man is the ſame, and <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in an agreeableneſs to them both) is the <hi>ſame,</hi> the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> muſt remain unchangeable as the meaſure of our moral actions: But as it is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Government in the world, it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that through the Mediation of Chriſt (who hath ſatisfied his Father for our breach of it) it is <hi>relaxed ſo</hi> as we are not dealt withal according to the tenour of the <hi>Law,</hi> in the matters of <hi>this</hi> life, or of that which is to <hi>come.</hi> I diſtinguiſh theſe two things, a Rule <hi>of Life,</hi> and a Rule <hi>for Life.</hi> A Rule <hi>for Life</hi> is expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>He that doeth them ſhall live in them.</hi> We are <hi>freed from</hi> the Law upon the <hi>later</hi> account: we are made <hi>free to it</hi> in regard to the <hi>former.</hi> That is, we are under the Law ſo as we are ſtill bound to <hi>live</hi> according to it: but we are delivered from it ſo as (through mercy, and the merits of Chriſt) we ſhall not be <hi>judged</hi> by it. There is <hi>Norma vitae:</hi> and <hi>Norma judicii.</hi> The Law is of force as a <hi>rule of Life,</hi> or Duty: but we are not under it as a <hi>rule of Judgement.</hi> We ſhall be <hi>judged</hi> ſaies St. <hi>James by the Law of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, <hi>according to my Goſpel.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God for this truth. Now that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God over the whole world is by the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> and not of <hi>Works</hi> (thus much being ſaid im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly only for light in the way), does appear as the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon</hi> in the Heavens. <hi>For God hath not left himſelf without witneſs, in that he does good, and gives us fruitful ſeaſons.</hi> Theſe are effects of his mercy, which he could not ſhew to the world as he does, if he dealt with it according to the Law of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62274:32"/>
                  <hi>Works.</hi> When <hi>Abraham</hi> pleads with God for <hi>Sodom</hi> that he would ſpare it if there were ten righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in it, it is manifeſt that he muſt account of Gods Government over the earth to be a Government of <hi>Grace. That the righteous be as the wicked, that be far from thee</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>ſhall not the judge of all the earth do right?</hi> If God ſhould <hi>do</hi> but <hi>right</hi> to the beſt of men according to the righteouſneſs of the Law of Works, there could be no ſuch pleading as this. Neither is there any righteous, <hi>no not one,</hi> ſaies the Scripture, nor could God have accepted of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf for <hi>one,</hi> had there been <hi>nine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, but upon the account of the Law of <hi>Grace.</hi> It is a righteouſneſs conſiſting in a condecency of his Goodneſs and Mercy, and not in the Rule of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrict Holineſs that <hi>Abraham</hi> intends. When the Prophets call upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> to repent and to <hi>do righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> that they may <hi>live,</hi> it is a perpetual diſcovery that God dealt not with them according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works. The Law admits no repentance, and there is no righteouſneſs that a man can <hi>live by</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Law.</hi> It is ſuch a righteouſneſs then they muſt mean ſtill, which is the ſame with the <hi>juſt mans faith,</hi> whereby it is ſaid he <hi>ſhall live;</hi> and that is <hi>the righteouſneſs of faith</hi> in the Goſpel, or <hi>righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which lies in a conformity to the law of Grace (See <hi>Mediocria,</hi> about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my Paper of the <hi>Covenants</hi>). We are righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous according to this Law, when we perform the condition: God is righteous according to it, when he accepts us thereupon, unto Pardon and Life. We have a moſt ſignal inſtance in the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> of theſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62274:32"/>two things I do here ſtand upon. If Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over the Heathen was not by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> how could the <hi>Ninevites</hi> by their repentance have diverted his judgments? And if this Law had not been <hi>connatural</hi> with <hi>faln</hi> man, ſo as to be <hi>written in their hearts,</hi> how could they truſt in God, that upon their forſaking ſin, and their turning to him, they ſhould find mercy, and be ſaved from deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Both theſe things (I ſay) have in this one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance their full evidence. And what think we of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> the Centurion and <hi>Roman,</hi> how could his <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Almes</hi> be <hi>accepted with God,</hi> if <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> as well as <hi>Paul,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> as well as <hi>Jew,</hi> were not under the ſame Government of Grace, when there is nothing we do but is imperfect, and lyable to a curſe by the Law of Works? And what ſhall we conclude then from both inſtances, but that which <hi>Peter</hi> upon conviction himſelf concludes? <hi>Of a truth I perceive that God is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of perſons: but in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted of him.</hi> There are three things go to a Law. That it be for the publick good, That it be the will of the Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, That it be promulgated to the ſubject. That the Law of Grace is good for the world there can be no queſtion; That it is Gods will the world ſhould be governed by it, appears by what is ſpoken, and that this Law hath been promulgated to mankind, appears both in the general notice of it in mens hearts (<hi>I will write my Law in their hearts</hi> ſaies God in the New Covenant, as diſtinguiſhed from that of the Jews), and in the expreſs declaration of God to our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62274:33"/>firſt Parents, that the <hi>ſeed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpents head,</hi> and in his Covenanting with <hi>Noah,</hi> which muſt be underſtood without diſpute in regard to them, and their poſterity. Now when ſuch a Law hath been promulgated to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to all the world, being to come of them, it muſt be proved that this Law is, or hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, or at ſome time, again repealed by God, or elſe muſt every man and woman in the world be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this government of God according to it, and conſequently be in a capacity of Salvation. I will to theſe Reaſonings, add one ſyllogiſm. It is <hi>not the hearers of the Law, but doers ſhall be juſtified.</hi> This is expreſs in one Verſe of the ſecond to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi> But ſame Heathen are doers of the Law, though not hearers of it. This is affirmed in the next Verſe. <hi>For when the Gentiles, which have not the Law, do by nature the things contained in the Law,</hi> with the reſt following. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome Heathen are juſtified and ſaved. If any cavil and ſay that no man is a doer of the Law, he muſt be anſwered that the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of ſuch a doing only as is ſuppoſed to be among the Jews that were godly, or Jews <hi>inwardly</hi> in the Verſes after. And I renew my argument. They that are doers of the Law accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſenſe of ſuch Texts as make the keeping the Commandments of God neceſſary to Salvation, ſuch as when Chriſt ſaies, <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandments;</hi> and ſuch as when the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>They that by patient continuance in well-doing ſeek for glory,</hi> ſhall have <hi>eternal life,</hi> that is, They who are doers of it, as all that are Jews
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62274:33"/>
                  <hi>inwardly</hi> and <hi>in the Spirit</hi> do keep it, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to wit, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>rigour</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> but according to <hi>acceptation</hi> by the equity of the Goſpel, They, I ſay, ſhall be juſtified and ſaved. But ſome Heathen are doers of the Law in this ſenſe, which is the ſenſe of the Apoſtle. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome Heathen are juſtified and ſaved. I confirm the <hi>Minor</hi> by the words enſuing, that we may be ſure we have the mind of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>Therefore if the uncircumciſion keep the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the Law, ſhall not his uncircumciſion be counted for circumciſion? And ſhall not uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion which is by nature if it fulfil the Law, judge thee, who by the letter and circumciſion doeſt break the Law?</hi> It follows that ſuch as theſe therefore are <hi>Jews inwardly,</hi> and <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> though they were not <hi>outward Jews,</hi> or <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> or <hi>of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> as is apparent in the words already, and the laſt Verſes. They that are Jews <hi>inwardly and in the Spirit</hi> then (I follow my argument), though not <hi>outwardly</hi> ſo and <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> do <hi>fulfill the Law</hi> in the ſenſe of this place and are juſtified. But ſuch are ſome of the Heathen here according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome Heathen are juſtified and ſaved. And what could be deſired more full and convincing, if it were not for the firſt Verſe which follows in the next Chapter, which does yet add ſuch abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confirmation to it, as I muſt profeſs my ſelf perfectly ſtriken with the evidence, as with a Beam of light never to be withſtood, or any more to be doubted. <hi>What advantage then hath the Jew</hi> above the Gentile? Theſe are the words.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62274:34"/>It cannot be imagined by me now, that this queſtion could be offered after he had ſaid thus much, if there were ſuch a difference between theſe two, as that one of them only was under a poſſibility of Salvation. It is brought in as an objection to his foregoing aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion in this ſenſe, that if this be true, there appears no difference in the matter, whether a man be Jew or Gentile, ſeeing he that hath the Law only written in his heart, and keeps it (that is in ſincerity), ſhall have the benefit and be ſaved, as well as he that hath it written in the Bible. The Apoſtle does as good as anſwer, This is true, yet is there a difference, <hi>Chiefly becauſe that unto the Jew were committed the Oracles of God.</hi> I interpret not theſe words, but give this paraphraſe. The Heathen were under the ſame law of Grace for life, as the Jews, but the Jews advantage was, that they had it in the ſecond promulgation with this priviledge of Ordinances: and our advantage is the like over them, that we have it in the third and laſt promulgation, by the Goſpel. I argue then once more. If this was the chief advantage the Jew had over the Gentile, that one had the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God and the other had not, then was there not this difference between them, as my Gentleman does make, that one is only in a <hi>ſtate of Nature,</hi> and the other in a <hi>ſtate of Grace;</hi> or that one was in a <hi>capacity,</hi> and the other under an <hi>impoſſibility</hi> of Salvation; for this were an advantage of a far greater nature. But this was the <hi>chief</hi> advantage. <hi>Chiefly becauſe—Ergo.</hi> The Objections againſt this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine are two. The one is from the Scriptures, which in many places in the New-Teſtament do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62274:34"/>quire faith in Chriſt, or believing the Goſpel, as the condition of Salvation. <hi>He that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> I anſwer, As the Apoſtle ſaies of the <hi>Law, Now we know that whatſoever things the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the Law:</hi> So ſay I of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> whatſoever things of this kind the Goſpel ſaith, it ſaith to thoſe that are under the Goſpel. Where the Goſpel is Preached, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is ſufficient, ſo that men wilfully reject it, ſuch are left without excuſe. The caſe of ſuch is dangerous indeed, and theſe Texts applicable to them. <hi>If ye believe not that I am he ye ſhall die in your ſins.</hi> But as for thoſe who never heard the Goſpel, or when the Revelation hath been inſufficient for ſuch conviction, the caſe (I hope) is otherwife, The caſe is (I think) as I have ſaid; and our good God will not <hi>require</hi> of any, <hi>more</hi> than he hath <hi>given.</hi> The other objection is from the authority of men, or of the Church more generally, that condemns this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But I count the teſtimony of Chriſtians in this point is for themſelves, and ſo partial; I ſuppoſe it taken again upon truſt, and followed by the moſt for want of light; I believe alſo that if they had had but this light only that I offer, they would have determined as I do. It is true, I grant, as our Church thinks, that there is no Religion <hi>by which</hi> a man can be ſayed, but one only, that is the true Religion; but this is a great truth here to be received, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in the root, according to what is ſaid, is indeed the univerſal Religion of mankind <hi>(whom therefore ye ignorantly worſhip, him declare I unto you):</hi> So that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe that live according to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62274:35"/>Reaſon, ſuch as <hi>Socrates, Heraclitus,</hi> and the like men, were <hi>Chriſtans,</hi> though they were not ſo <hi>called,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Juſtin</hi> the holy Martyr in his Apology, whatſoever Ancients beſides we have for us. Which doctrine nevertheleſs (to ſalve moſt fully the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Article of our Church at firſt mentioned) is not once to be thought on, or harboured, but as it is compatible with this certain Poſition, that there is no way (for all that) under Heaven whereby a man or woman is, or was, or can be ſaved, but in and through the only <hi>Name</hi> and mediation of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>For other foundation can no man lay than that is laid, which is Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the fourth place, I muſt require a better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation from this Author, how every man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that hath the Goſpel preached to them, are brought into ſuch a ſtate of grace, as to have that aſſiſtance from the Spirit of God which enables them to believe, and many of them effectually unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and yet that it is the Believer only is the Object of that promiſe that God will <hi>give his Spirit to them that ask him.</hi> There are two of his Chapters where he enumerates the effects of the Spirit, and he does in both make faith to be one and the chief of thoſe effects (that he may not find here any eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion): yet does he make faith the condition of that promiſe. How will he come off here? Untill a man be a Believer, or have faith, the promiſe of Gods gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Spirit belongs not to him, and yet is faith (and teachableneſs in order to it) an effect of the Spirit. That which is promiſed on a condition, is not obtained but by our performance of the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62274:35"/>himſelf argues ſomewhere. If Faith then be the <hi>thing promiſed,</hi> how can it be the <hi>condition</hi> of the Promiſe? If the Spirit that works Faith, or the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in regard to this effect is promiſed to the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then is Faith made a condition for obtaining <hi>it ſelf,</hi> when it is made ſo, for obtaining the <hi>Spirit</hi> that <hi>gives</hi> it. If we muſt believe that we may have the Spirit, how comes Faith to be the effect of having it? To be the condition which is antecedent to it, and to be the effect alſo which follows it, is methinks incompoſſible. He may ſhiſt perhaps, and diſtinguiſh. There is a Faith that makes a man a Chriſtian or his <hi>Believer:</hi> and a faith that makes a man <hi>holy</hi> and is ſaving. The one may be the condition of the other. Well, I will ask him then of the former, Is that faith I pray, the effect of a mans own ſtrength or freewill: or of the Spirit? If he ſay the firſt, what thinks he of that ſaying of our Lord, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing,</hi> that is, nothing to any ſaving purpoſe (to uſe the apt words of this Author otherwhere) when it is <hi>ſomething</hi> I think to <hi>purpoſe</hi> to do <hi>that</hi> as ſhall qualifie a man to be the Object of this promiſe, that God will give him his Spirit upon his asking, and the promiſe otherwiſe did not belong to him: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing this Gentleman thinks it <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> to allow ſo much without grace, and therefore does he ſet up his common grace to avoid that danger. If it be not of our ſelves, but of the Spirit, then have we here one of his Operations, (though the Spirit is promiſed in <hi>Luke</hi> in regard to all its effects and operations, if that which the Author ſaies in two Chapters about it, be valid) and ſo the difficulty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62274:36"/>How ſhall a man have the Spirit for this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or effect before faith, and yet faith be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Spirit and its operations? If he ſay that the <hi>grace</hi> which he calls <hi>common,</hi> or the <hi>Spirit</hi> as <hi>not promiſed,</hi> does work in a man truly one ſort of faith, or ſo much of a ſaving faith, as goes to the condition of the promiſe: and that another ſort of faith then, or ſo much more as is lacking to our faith, does flow (as the effect only thereof) from the promiſe after, when we perform this condition, he will be put very hard to it in ſuch a work as was that of <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion, and be forced to more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity than enough, in ſo critical a determination.</p>
               <p>In the fifth place, I have one argument to advance againſt this Doctrine of his, which is known <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> I will urge but one, becauſe it is the common cauſe, and he may find out as many more as he will in others. It is this. If there be that grace which he calls <hi>common</hi> vouchſafed to all under the Goſpel without any difference of election, ſo that there is the ſame and no other prepared for him that believes, and for him that believes not, which common grace then is left to the liberty of the will of every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual perſon to co-operate with it or not; and as a man does ſo, or does not, he brings himſelf into a ſtate of Salvation, or remains in a ſtate of wrath (this is the opinion), then muſt Man himſelf, or then muſt the Will of every man for himſelf, make the difference between him and another. But this, according to the judgement of moſt after <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is flat againſt the Scripture, <hi>Who hath made thee to daffer from another, and what is there, O man, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62274:36"/>thou haſt not received?</hi> I muſt add by way of ſtrength to the Argument, that upon this Hypotheſis it follows, that, that which is the <hi>leſs</hi> only, or leaſt conducing to mans Salvation is attributed to <hi>God,</hi> and that which is the <hi>greater</hi> and moſt conducive thereunto is aſcribed to <hi>man himſelf.</hi> It is more to <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>repent,</hi> than it is to have <hi>power</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and repent. The promiſe of Life and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not made to him that is <hi>enabled</hi> to believe, but to him that <hi>does</hi> believe, and obey the Goſpel. Now by the <hi>Arminian</hi> doctrine there is this grace care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provided, which ſhall enable every man to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and repent, ſo that the fault ſhall not lye on God if they do not, but on a mans own will: but the <hi>will</hi> or <hi>willing</hi> it ſelf muſt ariſe from that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which they are as careful to reſerve unto man. That which is the <hi>leſſer</hi> thing then (I ſay) the <hi>abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> (through divine Help, Aſſiſtance or Grace which is ſufficient for the impowring every one) to <hi>believe</hi> and be ſaved, is aſcribed to <hi>God,</hi> and acknowledged from him: but that which is the <hi>greater,</hi> which is the chief, that which does the work, the act it ſelf of willing, of believing and performing the terms of the Goſpel, is made the effect of <hi>mans</hi> own <hi>free-will.</hi> And yet farther to confirm the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The <hi>power to do</hi> is one thing, and the <hi>will and doing</hi> another; The <hi>grace</hi> one thing, and the <hi>co-operating</hi> with it another. If we have <hi>power</hi> now or aſſiſtance only from <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>will</hi> be of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> then is there <hi>ſomething,</hi> even this willing it ſelf, this believing it ſelf, this will to believe (or co-operating with this common grace) that is the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62274:37"/>greateſt thing, <hi>which we have not received,</hi> but is of our ſelves, or from our own ſtrength. I do not doubt but I may preſs this yet more cloſely if this Author ſhould give the occaſion; and I muſt adviſe him heartily to be very conſiderate, what he anſwers to this argument; becauſe I have pickt it out as that which I take to be the moſt momentous of any which are ordinarily urged by the Orthodox in this matter. I will cloſe it up with that Text, <hi>Work out your ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with fear and trembling,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle. This implies that a man hath power, or that if he will work he <hi>can.</hi> It is in vain to exhort any to do that which is not in their power. That which is <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>[the power to do if we will]</hi> is I count in <hi>man:</hi> but that which is the greater <hi>[the willing and doing]</hi> is <hi>aliunde,</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as it appears in the words following. <hi>For it is God that worketh in us to will and to do of his good pleaſure.</hi> So contrary are my apprehenſions here to this Gentlemans. A man muſt have <hi>power</hi> (he thinks) by all means from God (to this end he brings in his common grace), but the <hi>will</hi> muſt be of himſelf. I think now quite otherwiſe that <hi>power</hi> is of <hi>nature,</hi> for that is the leſs: and to reduce that power unto act, <hi>to will and to do,</hi> that is of <hi>grace,</hi> for that is the greater, or that which is moſt. <hi>It is not of him that willeth and runneth</hi> (to wit, that he wills and and runs, ſaies the Father) <hi>but of God that ſheweth mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſixth place then, I have a mind to tell him ſome little of what I think of this grace he calls <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> The term <hi>Grace</hi> (we muſt know) which is all one with <hi>Favour,</hi> does import a reſpect ſhewn to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62274:37"/>ſome which is not to <hi>others,</hi> and does horein differ from <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which <hi>reſpects no perſon</hi> above another, but does diſtribute that which is due to every one without partiality. It is otherwiſe in Grace, for there are two things quite contrary muſt go to the making any thing a matter of <hi>Favour;</hi> it muſt be a thing not due, or of right, for then there is place to exerciſe <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but not <hi>Grace,</hi> and it muſt be given out of <hi>Choice,</hi> it muſt be vouchſafed to <hi>one</hi> and not <hi>another,</hi> when it is <hi>due</hi> to <hi>neither.</hi> When this Author then, and the Schools do ſpeak of a Grace that is Common and Univerſal, they ſeem to be teachers of ſomething wherein they underſtand not <hi>what they ſpeak, or whereof they affirm.</hi> There is the grace of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or that Grace which the Goſpel publiſhes, <hi>which brings Salvation to all men,</hi> the <hi>Objective</hi> grace of it, conſiſting in <hi>that faithful ſaying worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt died for ſinners,</hi> or that thoſe that believe and repent ſhall be ſaved, or that God is Good, and thoſe who turn to him, though they have ſinned, ſhall find merey, which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole two Teſtaments, and that indeed is. Univerſal, and belongs alike to all the world. There is no man or woman, or no people but they are under the Law of Grace (purchaſed by Chriſt) for life and ſalvation, I have ſaid; and ſay, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of this Grace, or the diſcovery of it, is ſo far uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal alſo, as there are none but by tradition from their Parents, or by ſome Teachers, as <hi>Noah</hi> was to the old world, teaching this Law (for there never was any other righteouſneſs ſince <hi>Adam</hi> fell, but of this Law only to ſave any), or by the dictates of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62274:38"/>their own hearts, did, or do underſtand it in ſome meaſure, ſo that if they live up to this Law accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the light only which they have, they are not only under the <hi>poſſibility,</hi> but in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of Salvation. This is a noble truth and worthy of God and his goodneſs, and I cannot part with it. But for that Grace which is the <hi>ſubjective</hi> grace of God, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thoſe operations of his Spirit that bring over the hearts of men to perform thoſe terms which this law of grace requires of us, To ſpeak of that as common and belonging to all, is (I ſay) to ſpeak of what this Author <hi>knowes not,</hi> becauſe theſe Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are for certain ſecret and indiſcernible; and to <hi>affirm</hi> of that which he knows not, what is inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the nature of what he ſpeaks. For if thoſe operations belong to all, and are not vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to ſome peculiar perſons only with diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from others, they are not <hi>Grace.</hi> This is ſo true, that when I ſay, the grace of the Goſpel which is <hi>Objective</hi> is univerſal to all mankind, if there were not other creatures beſides men, to whom Redemption and Reconciliation is not vouchſafed as to us, it could not be called <hi>Grace.</hi> It were a <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> and infinitely great, but not properly <hi>Grace.</hi> There is a world of fallen Spirits, as well as men, and there was nothing due to the one or the other but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: yet when no kindneſs was due, the Son of God came from Heaven, and took on him our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to redeem us and not them, this makes the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Chriſt to be grace to us. And now when the benefit, or benefits purchaſed by Chriſt are applied to particular perſons by the operations of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62274:38"/>Spirit working Faith and Repentance (which are the conditions upon which they are applied) in ſome perſons and not in others, if theſe operations were indeed common and vouchaſafed to thoſe that believe and repent <hi>not,</hi> as well as thoſe that <hi>do,</hi> this Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation were not of Grace. Where there is none <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed,</hi> there is no <hi>election.</hi> If one be not <hi>preferred,</hi> and not another, or before another, there is no <hi>Grace.</hi> The ground of this opinion of ſufficient grace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, hath aroſe as I conjecture, from an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion that the help or aſſiſtance of God (which we call grace) is converſant about the <hi>Power</hi> which is in man, ſo that a man is <hi>enabled</hi> thereby only to act, but the <hi>Will</hi> or actual willing is of <hi>himſelf.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> I remember, does tell us, that this was the conceit of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and he ſets himſelf therefore to prove, that Grace is converſant about the <hi>will;</hi> it is Grace (ſaies he) that <hi>inclines the will,</hi> it is of God to work in us <hi>to Will and to Do</hi> of his own good pleaſure. And indeed I do not ſee how it can conſiſt with the nature of the Spirit of God, who is God, that is, with the ſimplicity of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is devoid of all compoſition, Subject and Accident, Power and Act, how any <hi>operation</hi> can be attributed to him, but in regard of ſome <hi>effect.</hi> If there be ſuch an operation then imagined, which is ſufficient only to produce ſuch an effect on man, but it is hindred by the reſiſtance of his will, here being no effect, there is no operation can be aſcribed to God, in whom there is but one eternal ſtanding Will, the Will being not taken for the <hi>Faculty</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but <hi>Act.</hi> Beſides this determination of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62274:39"/>Schools that God is a <hi>Pure Act,</hi> and can be capable of no new operations, but only as he is denominated an Agent from ſuch continued new effects (wherein my own underſtanding, I confeſs, muſt be ever at a loſs); there is this plain thing to be thought on by every body, that no wiſe perſon who is not deſtitute of <hi>power,</hi> does <hi>operate</hi> without <hi>Effect.</hi> 'Tis true, that the Scripture ſomewhere ſpeaks of <hi>reſiſting the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and <hi>receiving his grace in vain:</hi> but this is not to be underſtood (I ſuppoſe) ſo, as if there were <hi>no</hi> effects wrought on ſuch ſouls, but that there are <hi>farther</hi> effects, ſaving effects, and it is to be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the obſtinacy or wickedneſs of their Wills, that thoſe effects are not wrought alſo. I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deliver here my opinion of this univerſal ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Grace which I find in the Schools, and in the <hi>Arminians,</hi> but confined to thoſe under the Goſpel by this Author; and I do think really it is an inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only to put off St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and to eſcape the condemnation of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> in a point, which in the ſubſtance of it, they judge fit to be maintained. The point is this, that if man does doe what lies in his power, God in his juſtice will give him his grace, <hi>Facienti quod in ſe eſt Deus non poteſt, nec debet denegare gratiam,</hi> which I mention the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee this Doctrine laid down in ſome good Books of late without ſuſpicion of <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> in it. Well! If any ſay now, that man by doing what he can of his own ſtrength does obtain Gods grace, this ſhall be <hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> and be anathamatized by the Schools themſelves: but if he ſay, that by doing <hi>through Gods grace</hi> what he can, he ſhall obtain (or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62274:39"/>merit) more grace, and ſo juſtification and life, it ſhall be the doctrine of the Church. Let it here be but ſuppoſed then, that God gives his <hi>Grace</hi> or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to <hi>All</hi> that they may act, and that which <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius</hi> would have, is brought in for good Doctrine without any hereſie at all in it; and this is the device of the <hi>Arminian</hi> from the Schools, which if it were in <hi>rerum naturae,</hi> as in mens <hi>Books,</hi> I do apprehend that <hi>Pelagius</hi> or <hi>Auſtine</hi> would have light upon it; and then would the one have received <hi>Pelagius</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with more candor, and the other would have defended it ſo cleverly, as never to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. But if this <hi>univerſal ſufficient grace</hi> was indeed never thought upon till after their time, I wonder not that <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Auſtine</hi> could not be agreed, but I do wonder that any who believe this knack ſhould make ſo much matter of it whether they agreed or no. I think it really but much at one to hold that every one hath <hi>power by Nature,</hi> as to affirm that all have <hi>Grace.</hi> If <hi>Grace</hi> be as common as <hi>Nature,</hi> why is it called Grace? Not that I ſee any hurt in holding <hi>Sufficient</hi> grace, provided that <hi>Effectual</hi> be held alſo. If <hi>univerſal</hi> grace be brought in for excluſion of <hi>ſpecial</hi> grace, I can by no means admit of it, for that ſome perſons have that grace from God whereby they are effectually wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſaved, and not others, is beyond diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If <hi>ſufficient</hi> grace <hi>common</hi> to all, and <hi>ſpecial</hi> too, be held ſo, as it be conceived that no man for all the one, does ever ſavingly believe and repent, or is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converted, till he have the other alſo, there is no <hi>hurt</hi> in it, but I ſee no <hi>need</hi> of it. What need is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62274:40"/>there of Grace only to bring us power, which we have already? There is no man ſhall be condemned for his <hi>cannot,</hi> but his <hi>will not.</hi> Every man then muſt have <hi>power.</hi> A man hath his faculties, his Underſtanding, his Will and his Executive power. the object is propoſed, His duty known; There is nothing to hinder, He may act if he will. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture indeed ſpeaks of a <hi>Cannot,</hi> that we <hi>can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> that we are <hi>dead</hi> in treſpaſſes and the like: but all theſe expreſſions put together comes to this, to wit, <hi>ſuch an indiſpoſition on the ſoul, as that a man certainly never will of himſelf.</hi> This is the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures <hi>cannot</hi> truly defined. (See <hi>Mediocria,</hi> in the Paper of Election), which otherwhere therefore is ordinarily called a <hi>will not.</hi> You <hi>will not come to me that you may have life.</hi> There is <hi>Natural</hi> power ſtill, where yet there is <hi>Moral</hi> impotency, as others have it. And it is no abſurd thing (I hope) to ſay a man can do what he can; that is, he can do, what he hath <hi>natural power</hi> to do. Here then I will ſtick, <hi>Power</hi> is of <hi>Nature</hi> (I ſaid it before), but to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert that power</hi> into act, is of <hi>Grace. Power</hi> is of <hi>Nature,</hi> but to <hi>Will</hi> and to <hi>Do,</hi> is of <hi>God.</hi> There is no people but have the Object (I count) and ſome light of it (in their meaſure) ſo that every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may live according to what he <hi>hath,</hi> and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted if he will. I grant this to the <hi>Pelagian,</hi> to the Schools, to the <hi>Arminian,</hi> that every one <hi>may,</hi> if they <hi>will: The Spirit ſaies come, and the Bride ſaies come, and whoſoever will let him come.</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I ſay more? Whoſoever will believe and repent, may believe and repent; whoſoever will be ſaved.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62274:40"/>may be ſaved. This I ſay with them, but I muſt then ſay again with the Orthodox, that if any <hi>will,</hi> it is of the grace of God. If <hi>he will,</hi> it is of Gods <hi>grace</hi> againſt <hi>Pelagius. No man cometh to me unleſs the Father draw him.</hi> If he <hi>will,</hi> it is of Gods <hi>ſpecial grace</hi> againſt the <hi>Arminian. But ye believe not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye are not of my ſheep. As many as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſalvation believed.</hi> In ſhort then, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will, <hi>may</hi> (or can): but no man <hi>will</hi> (though he can) without <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> grace. Here is the deciſion of this great controverſie. And as for the <hi>Arminian</hi> grace, what good of that, which if one had it not, he ſhould have pleaded a Cannot, and been excuſed: but by having it he muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned?</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, ſeeing I perceive this Gentleman is liſted for <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> I care not if I tell him yet ſome more of my heart about it. I am pretty ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how things hang together. If God intend to give grace and ſalvation to a few particular perſons, it is ſuitable that ſuch only ſhould be redeemed; and if this grace be free as decreed abſolutely to theſe, it is ſuitable the will be not free, ſo as to be able to chooſe or refuſe it; It is then agreeable that thoſe be kept by the ſame almighty power to ſalvation. Here are the five points on one ſide. On the other hand, If a man that hath grace, is to take heed leſt he fall, it is ſuitable that grace be ſuch as might be refuſed at firſt, as well as it may (after) be loſt; That the will conſequently is free, ſo as to co-operate with it or not; That Chriſt therefore hath purchaſed but the ſame grace for one as well as another; That
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62274:41"/>Election then be of ſuch perſons as uſe their own li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Gods grace, as they ought, when thoſe that do not, are juſtly rejected and condemned. I muſt declare now, I find here no averſion in my mind againſt the laſt ſet of opinions, but rather ſome diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to the former. I feel my genius more afraid of a captivity by that we call Orthodoxiſm, than by any thing elſe; which makes me come with leſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to read <hi>Vorſtius,</hi> than <hi>Rutherford,</hi> or <hi>Twiſſe.</hi> I have no <hi>preocupation,</hi> therefore I am ſure on my <hi>affections,</hi> whatſoever I have on my <hi>judgement</hi> in theſe points. Nevertheleſs there is a chain laid on my ſoul from the holy Scriptures, which holds it faſt. The chain conſiſts of theſe links, Perſonal <hi>Election, Regeneration,</hi> and that, <hi>Few ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Theſe three Doctrines I muſt ſay, are ſo concatenated (in my mind) one with another, that ſo long as any one of them will hold, it is in vain to make any attempt to get looſe from either of the other. I cannot but confeſs many times they are grievous to my mind, and I could wiſh they were otherwiſe, but if they are the dictates of holy writ, I muſt pray to God to forgive my reluctancy, and ſubmit to them. I have had indeed ſometimes in my ſoul ſome other notion of Election than is expreſſed ordinarily by others. I have lookt methinks on the deliberations of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty with his Son from eternity (to ſpeak after the manner of men), to be how they ſhould be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied moſt in the Salvation of man: and there are two waies to that end, the <hi>way of Works,</hi> and the <hi>way of Grace.</hi> If man being made after Gods image, does live according to the law of his Creation, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62274:41"/>ſtand in that eſtate he muſt be happy and glorifie his Maker in a method of <hi>works:</hi> but if he be left to himſelf, and fall, and be recovered by the rdempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Son, and then have a new Law for his faln condition, and continued help, to live accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, then ſhall God glorifie himſelf in mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, by the methods of his moſt wonderful <hi>grace.</hi> Now what if Gods election from eternity be nothing elſe but this deſign, that mans ſalvation ſhall be in a way of <hi>Grace,</hi> and not of <hi>Works?</hi> He hath <hi>choſen us in him</hi> (ſaies the Text) <hi>that we ſhould be holy.</hi> I put the Emphaſis on the words, <hi>in him.</hi> It is Chriſt hath procured the new Law, according to which we may be holy and accepted, when elſe we could not be holy by the <hi>Law</hi> of our <hi>Nature;</hi> and ſo it is not <hi>by the works of righteouſneſs which we have done,</hi> or works by <hi>that Law,</hi> but by the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or his aſſiſtance to perform the <hi>Law of Grace;</hi> ſo that when it is ſaid other-where, <hi>Not of works leſt any ſhould boaſt,</hi> it is add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>For we are his workmanſhip created in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to good works.</hi> We were created at firſt to a law of righteouſneſs, but this being once broken, unleſs we had had a new Law purchaſed by Chriſt, and a new Creation through him, we could not have been righteous any more; ſo that it is not of works, which are properly mans own, according to the Law of his <hi>Nature,</hi> but of thoſe which we are created to in Chriſt Jeſus; to wit, thoſe which are called the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God</hi> (as being of his invention or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment) in oppoſition to the <hi>Law,</hi> that we are ſaved. This is typed in the <hi>children of the Fleſh,</hi> and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62274:42"/>the <hi>children of the Promiſe;</hi> and this may be the meaning of theſe words, <hi>It is not of him that willeth and runneth</hi> (that is, it is not in <hi>the way of works</hi>) <hi>but of God that ſheweth mercy</hi> (that is, but of <hi>Grace</hi>). This is delivered here, I know, roughly and darkly: yet may it ſerve another man to think upon, when I my ſelf do not purſue it. There is in the Papers called the <hi>Middle way,</hi> ſomething of this in that of <hi>Election</hi> p. 15, 16. and ſomething more accurately in that of the <hi>Covenants</hi> p. 6, <hi>ad</hi> 13. There is another notion of Election; To wit, the chooſing of perſons or a people to a Church-ſtate, or the priviledge of Ordinances, and ſo unto the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar government of God or Chriſt over them upon that account. <hi>He hath given his Statutes to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>he hath not done ſo to other Nations.</hi> Thus <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> is the firſt <hi>Elect</hi> we read of. <hi>Thou didſt chooſe</hi> Abraham, <hi>and broughtſt him out of</hi> Ur, <hi>and madeſt a Covenant with him,</hi> in <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> That was by way of preamble to Gods gathering a Church out of his ſeed, who was to be his people. Hence is he ſaid in ſeveral places to have choſen them, not for their deſerts, or their number, but <hi>becauſe he loved thy Fathers, therefore he choſe their ſeed after them;</hi> and hence have they the titles of a <hi>peculiar people,</hi> and a <hi>choſen generation,</hi> with many the like expreſſions. In the New-Teſtament likewiſe we find thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Goſpel have the ſame titles, They are ſaid to be engrafted into the Jews <hi>Olive,</hi> that is, into their external Covenant and Church-ſtate, and to be a <hi>choſen generation</hi> (as the Jews were) a <hi>royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> and a <hi>peculiar people,</hi> inſomuch as when the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62274:42"/>Apoſtle writes to a whole Church, he calls them <hi>Elect,</hi> as well as <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> And the <hi>faith of Gods elect</hi> may perhaps be thus interpreted the <hi>Chriſtian faith.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>is the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe God is the Lord, and the people whom he hath choſen for his own inheritance.</hi> Theſe notions I mention, but muſt travail no further in the ſearch of them, becauſe I am held by the other doctrines I have named, <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and That <hi>few ſhall be ſaved.</hi> For if theſe two Doctrines be not capable of ſome other notion alſo than what is commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by them, they muſt fix me in the like recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved notion of Election. If there is ſuch a thing then (in the firſt place) as Regeneration, that is a work of grace on the ſouls of ſome perſons whereby they are begotten again to a holy life, as well as to the relation of the children of God, then is Election, I muſt ſay, <hi>actuated</hi> in ſuch perſons. The Schools di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Actual</hi> Election, and this work of ſaving converſion or effectual vocation they call <hi>Actual election.</hi> Election is the preparation of effectual grace for ſome perſons that they may be ſaved, and not for others. This effectual grace then vouchſafed to any particular perſon in, or for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, is the <hi>execution</hi> of <hi>Election.</hi> Such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance have theſe doctrines upon one another, that we ſhall not need to enquire farther what is Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we underſtand, and prove by this effect Regeneration, better than by any mans definition, or arguments. If we cannot come off therefore about <hi>Regeneration,</hi> as well as <hi>Election,</hi> we muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the one, in our judgement concerning
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62274:43"/>the other. For the helping us out here, this Author hath ſaid ſomething; That to be regenerate is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Diſciple of Chriſt, and that is to be brought into the Church or Church-ſtate, which agrees with the ſecond Notion before of Election. He that is a Diſciple muſt be baptized, and to be baptized is to be both again by water, and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into Chriſt, and he that is but externally <hi>in Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>new creature,</hi> as one of that <hi>world to come</hi> in the ſecond to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which is ſaid to be <hi>put in ſubjection to Chriſt,</hi> that is the Chriſtian Church under the Goſpel. Agreeably hereunto this Author tells us out of Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> that the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes</hi> of the very Jewiſh Church were called <hi>recens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati</hi> upon this ſame account. Regeneration then may be a <hi>Relative</hi> term only, or but <hi>Relative grace,</hi> whether in regard to a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>External</hi> relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What this may do now with others, I know not. This Author does make Regeneration to conſiſt in a <hi>Real work</hi> on the ſoul as well as others, while he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines the regenerate man to be one that does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become <hi>a Diſciple,</hi> but a <hi>ſincere Diſciple</hi> of Chriſt; for this includes that effectual grace which proceeds from Election. And yet if we could get off from both theſe Doctrines, <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Regeneration,</hi> there remains farther the third Doctrine, <hi>That few ſhall be ſaved,</hi> from which there is no man I ever yet read, <hi>Arminian</hi> or <hi>Antiarminian</hi> that ſought an eſcape. They are words out of our Lords own mouth <hi>[Few there be that find it],</hi> and the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt that ſet them down could not be miſtaken in Chriſts meaning; There is no mans heart can ſerve
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62274:43"/>him to think ſo, becauſe they were inſpired in what they writ, If this be a truth then, that few ſhall be ſaved, it is a truth that it is Gods <hi>will</hi> that few ſhall be ſaved; and conſequently if his <hi>will,</hi> his <hi>decree.</hi> If it be <hi>Gods decree</hi> then, that <hi>few ſhall be ſaved,</hi> I cannot be ſolicitous any farther about Perſonal or Abſolute Election, There appears to me really to be a greater diſhonour put upon Gods <hi>goodneſs</hi> and infinite mercy to make him decree ſalvation to all, on ſuch conditions, as a few perſons only (left to their liberty) ſhall thereupon be able to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, than can be caſt meerly on his <hi>juſtice</hi> or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, to decree that grace, or ſuch grace to theſe few perſons, that ſhall effectually bring them to that end. And what though, Salvation ſometimes be taken alſo as Election in Scripture, in reference to a mans being brought into the <hi>Ark,</hi> that is, into the Church, and ſo we are ſaid to be ſaved by baptiſm, as it is ſaid, <hi>Save your ſelves from this untoward generation,</hi> and as they which <hi>were added to the Church</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>ſaved,</hi> and as <hi>ſalvation</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>of the Jews?</hi> What mans reaſon can ſerve him to believe that Chriſt ſpeaks of this <hi>ſalvation?</hi> If it could, Are there not more that come into the Church, than are eternally ſaved? There is doubtleſs a <hi>double</hi> Election and Salvation in Scripture, <hi>Temporal</hi> in this ſenſe before ſpoken, in relation to a Church-ſtate, and Chriſts government of us by the Goſpel: and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> in this ſenſe of Salvation whereof Chriſt is ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he ſaies, <hi>And few there be that find it.</hi> Such is our Election, and ſuch is this Salvation; Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>from</hi> Eternity, and ſalvation <hi>to</hi> eternity, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62274:44"/>both meet in Regeneration. For regeneration, is Actual Election, and Inchoate Salvation. <hi>There are three that bear record in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>three in Earth,</hi> ſaies St. <hi>John.</hi> Theſe three <hi>agree in one,</hi> and thoſe three <hi>are one.</hi> I will ſay ſo here, There are three things that bear record in Scripture, <hi>Election, Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> and That <hi>few ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Theſe three <hi>agree in one,</hi> that is, in their teſtimony for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox againſt the <hi>Arminian,</hi> and ſo for St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> againſt this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. And theſe three <hi>are one,</hi> in their concatenati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one with another. Election is the preparation of that ſpecial effectual grace which works our regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and our regeneration is the begetting in us that life, that ſpiritual life which runs on to eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Effectual grace is the Execution of Election, and entrance of Salvation. Grace is glory in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,</hi> and Glory is grace in <hi>full age,</hi> at maturity, or in conſummation. Theſe things are thus linked, and this is the Chain that holds me. I do endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make the chain as caſie as I can, and get as much room in it as I can by going the middle way, but I am held under it. If you cannot break every link, you ſhall never break any one of them; or if you could, it were in vain to do it. And now would I look into this Gentlemans heart how it can ſerve him to meditate a reply to theſe things. I will tell him in his own words the iſſue it muſt come to. <hi>But what if the Scriptures teach, that the promiſe of Regenerating grace are</hi> made <hi>only to thoſe that are abſolutely</hi> elected <hi>to glory</hi> (This hereby, I count, is proved in the very root of it)? <hi>I anſwer</hi> (ſaies
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62274:44"/>he) <hi>If this can be once ſhewn, I have done; or if it can be made to appear but probable by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, I ſhall begin to ſuſpect all my reaſoning againſt it. For I heartily believe the Scriptures to be the word of God, and all my Reaſonings ſhall ſubmit to this one Propoſition, Whatſoever God hath ſaid that is true.</hi> This is ſaid well, and ſo well ſaid as I will end this Chapter with it, and I think we muſt both end the Controverſie with it. <hi>They ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them: for he is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings; and thoſe that are with him, are called, and faithful, and choſen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Reſiſtibility or Irreſiſtibility of the Spirits Operations, in reference to his laſt Chapter.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Come to the Authors laſt Chapter, which is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>meaſure of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus operations.</hi> And I obſerve here the <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> of it, the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it, and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Controverſie</hi> of it, it may be reduced to two Queſtions. Whether the Operations of Gods Spirit be by way of <hi>moral ſwaſion,</hi> or <hi>phyſical ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</hi> and whether theſe Operations, or the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual grace of God on the heart in a Sinners conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be <hi>irreſiſtible?</hi> I will content my ſelf with the laſt point, unto which the other I conceive, may be reduced; and this is a controverſie (as others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore)
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62274:45"/>which hath the <hi>Arminians</hi> on one ſide, and <hi>Synod of Dort</hi> on the other. The Dr. is for the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> we may be ſure, and this Author for the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> The only thing to be underſtood between both, is, what they mean by the term <hi>irreſiſtitle?</hi> If the Dr. hath received by it an apprehenſion, as if the work of grace on the ſoul was ſuch as diſarmed the will of its liberty, and left it no power of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to that ſaying which this Author quotes for his, that <hi>the Will cannot make uſe of that grace which it can refuſe,</hi> the Doctor is out; for the Will cannot be without natural liberty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing or willing, and if that beraken away, it is deſtroyed: but if herein he be miſeited, or his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention perverted, and he does hold only that this work is irreſiſtible in regard to the event, that is, where that grace which is effectual, is given, it will infallibly have its effect, the Doctor is in the right. Again, if this Author, by <hi>reſiſtible,</hi> underſiands, that where this grace is given, or where the Spirit thus operates, the will hath not only <hi>power</hi> of reſiſting, but many times <hi>does</hi> reſiſt, ſo that Chriſt may ſay but to any one who hath <hi>that</hi> grace, <hi>I would, and you would not</hi> this Author is out; for this ſpecial ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual grace flowes from the decree of Election, and can neverfail: but if he mean by <hi>reſiſtible</hi> only that though the will be carried by it, and <hi>does not reſiſt,</hi> yet it hath <hi>power</hi> ſtill <hi>to reſiſt,</hi> ſo that its liberty for all that cannot be loſt, he is in the right. The <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> and this <hi>grace</hi> that flows from it, is not conſiſtent with a <hi>contrary event,</hi> but they are conſiſtent with a <hi>contrary power,</hi> a power, I mean,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62274:45"/>to do the contrary. They will certainly and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly carry the Will, becauſe Gods will muſt ſtand, and his decree cannot fail, but the power of doing the contrary, (or not doing) is not inconſiſtent with the certainty of the thing being done. The <hi>power of doing otherwiſe,</hi> and <hi>doing otherwiſe</hi> are two things. Where the Decree, and Grace is, they infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly produce the effect, that we ſhall not <hi>do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe:</hi> but the <hi>power of doing otherwiſe</hi> is untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The thing is <hi>neceſſary</hi> in regard to the <hi>decree,</hi> and it is <hi>free</hi> or contingent in regard to this <hi>power</hi> in man <hi>to reſiſt.</hi> Man hath <hi>power to reſiſt,</hi> ſo grace is <hi>reſiſtible:</hi> but it is <hi>irreſiſtable</hi> in regard to the <hi>act</hi> or <hi>effect.</hi> When the power then and liberty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, this work of God upon the ſoul is not by ſuch a way of phyſical operation, as the raiſing one from the dead, or as creation is, but it is by ſuch a way as is ſuitable to a free creature, who is brought to act out of election; it is by <hi>Argument</hi> and the <hi>Word,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Divine motion.</hi> It is therefore, for ought I ſee, neither by meer phyſical operation, nor only by moral <hi>ſwaſion,</hi> but by an omnipotent <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</hi> By ſuch a ſweet attemperation to the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as will infallibly carry the Will, and yet not by compulſion. If you ask me any farther, I will be exculed. I remember Chriſt ſpeaking of this work, compares it to the <hi>wind</hi> which we cannot perceive, either <hi>whence it comes,</hi> or <hi>whither it goes.</hi> And <hi>if we cannot tell the things that are with us, how ſhall our veſſels comprehend the wayes of the moſt High;</hi> the workings, the manner, and the meaſure of the working, of the Spirit of God? I muſt add this only
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62274:46"/>which is open, Let the term <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> be expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed right, I am for the Doctor; Let the term <hi>reſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> be expounded right, I am for this Author. When I agree then with both of them, if they both will agree with me, we muſt grow all friends in this point.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Chapter it comes to this ſumm, which I can give here in the words of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. The holy ſpirit of God doth in that manner work his graces in us, that they are ſtill the genuine effects of the Evidence and Motives of the Goſpel; Of the natural uſe of our faculties, the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and will; and of our own care and diligence in uſing the external means of grace. His operations in us make us capable of recovering our ſelves by degrees; and all the while there is no ſenſible diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, and the natural operatious of our minds; and yet we are ſure we have his aſſiſtance, and help in all the good we do, and without it we can do nothing at all to ſaving purpoſes. This is the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which if no inferences but Orthodox be drawn from it, I take to be ſound. We have then ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it, which is alſo very good. There is but a little of it, but if he had been <hi>more</hi> in that, and <hi>leſs</hi> in quarrels with the Doctor, it had yet been all better. And ſo God bleſs the hopeful Author in his Studies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:62274:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Authors Calumniations of Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and ſome reply to them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Having thus done with the Book, there are ſome paſſages require my reflection upon them, for the Doctors vindication. The Doctor is accuſed of <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> of <hi>Error.</hi> It is fit that ſome thing ſhould be ſaid in reference to the <hi>two lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> though it be but a rudeneſs to go about to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer any thing to the <hi>former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt therefore I will ſay this only. If the Doctor hath expreſſed any thing darkly, that this Author cannot make <hi>ſenſe</hi> of it: ſuch a place, or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage as to him, is to go for nothing. That is all in civility to be ſaid of it.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, There is one inſtance I will menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about Election. The Doctor in one place of his Book, ſpeaking (I ſuppoſe) to a prophane perſon, yet preſuming on his Election, tells him, <hi>He cannot believe his Election any otherwiſe, but as God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals it by the effects,</hi> that is, untill he believe, and repents he cannot conclude he is Elected. In another place ſpeaking (I ſuppoſe) to the tender ſerious Chriſtian, who is yet in trouble about his Election, he ſaies, <hi>He cannot juſtly doubt of his Election, until he be in ſuch a condition, as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is impoſſible that the effects of Election ſhould be wrought in him.</hi> This the Author makes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: but it is only the diſtinguiſhing between
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62274:47"/>theſe two things, A <hi>not concluding,</hi> and A <hi>concluding not,</hi> and the Doctor is cleared. The man who ſees not the effects of Election on his heart, and in his life, cannot conclude that he is elected (here is the <hi>not concluding,</hi> which ought to be): And the man that ſees them not, cannot conclude for all that, that he is not Elected, becauſe they may be wrought in him before he dies, (here is the <hi>concluding not,</hi> which muſt be avoided). So the one is rebuked, and the other ſupported (as they ſhould both be). Such are the Doctors contradictions.</p>
               <p>For the third, which is the Doctors Errors, I muſt diſtinguiſh of Error. There is <hi>Human</hi> Error, Error <hi>common to man,</hi> It is the nature of man to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to mulake, to be deceived, to err, ſaies the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: and there are <hi>Pernicious</hi> Errors. This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans accuſations are of both ſorts.</p>
               <p>For the former ſort, There is two or three places where this Author is very confident upon the Doctor for his ſaying that the Spirit is given to us in his <hi>Perſon</hi> as well as in his <hi>Effects,</hi> which methinks I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſs, becauſe I do not know well whether the Error be in the Doctor, or in this Author, or in my ſelf. I am apt to think, that it is <hi>too much</hi> to ſay that the Spirit dwelleth perſonally in any man, though we are ſaid to be the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt: and that it is <hi>too little</hi> to ſay he is given on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his giſts, graces, or effects. I would ſay rather, that the Spirit is given <hi>it ſelf for</hi> theſe Effects. I look upon the Spirit of Chriſt to be given to us for a principle of life and union with our Head, from whom we have (through this Spirit) the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62274:47"/>of all ſaving influence unto a holy life. It is the received opinion that there is an habitual righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs infuſed by God in the ſoul for our juſtification according to the Schools, or according to our Divines, for our Regeneration; and that this is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life and power in the ſoul unto holy operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I muſt confeſs here I do not receive this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I have it ſomewhere in my <hi>Mediocria,</hi> I think more cautiouſly, but I do really believe no infuſion of habits. I count that the Spirit by a motion on the Will, exciting it to act, does incline it to farther acts by the impreſſion which is made, and that the habit then is acquired by the iteration of thoſe acts and delight in them, or love to them, ſhed abroad in our hearts by the ſame <hi>Holy Ghoſt given to us.</hi> I do believe conſequently, that it is the Spirit it ſelf dwelling in us (as the Scripture underſtands its own expreſſion) which is that principle of life from whoſe conſtant ſecret and unperceptable aid, does proceed all thoſe actions which are holy and good, and acceptable to God. I do believe there is a time when Chriſt gives his Spirit to every one of his Elect, for uniting him to himſelf as his head, and that this union is effected immediately by that communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that through this Spirit all vital influence muſt be derived to us. I cannot frame my ſelf to ſay the Spirit is <hi>perſonally</hi> in us, but he is in Chriſts members as a <hi>principle of life</hi> and ſpiritual action, and as the formal band of that union which we have with him. Now ye are the body of Chriſt, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in particular. As the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that body
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62274:48"/>are one body; ſo alſo is Chriſt. I cannot tell well therefore how to brook ſome expreſſions as I find ſomewhere in this Author, and in another before him, that when the Scripture ſpeaks of our having the Spirit of Chriſt, and having it ſo as to be led by him, and if we have not the Spirit of Chriſt, we are none of his, they are willing to interpret the having Chriſts Spirit, to be only the being of his temper and and diſpoſition, which is the bringing down the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to our ordinary converſe, and ſeems to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy. I hope theſe men do believe the Chriſtian faith, and do reverence his myſteries. And there are theſe three of them, The myſterie of the Trinity, The myſterie of the Incarnation, and the Myſtical Union between Chriſt and his Church. It is true that Chriſt is not a Natural head but a Political, as oppoſed to natural, but not as oppoſed to myſtical. He is a Political head as he governs us, and as we are in ſubjection to him: but he is alſo a Myſtical head, vouchſafing to us that ſpiritual influence which enables us to obey him. He governs us, and ſo is our head: but he governs us by his Spirit which is infuſed (though I think no habit be); and when we are lead by this Spirit, as there is Rule, there is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and this Union muſt be Real and Myſtical, and not that which is Political only. Suppoſe a man wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe head was high as the Heavens, yet ſo long as the ſame ſoul animates all the members, the feet as in the head, it is one man: Chriſt our head is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and we on earth; yet as the ſame Spirit is in us which is in him, the head and members make one dy, nay in the words of the Scripture, <hi>one Chriſt. O</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:62274:48"/>Agrippa <hi>believeſt thou the Prophets?</hi> O thou Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Book againſt Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Believeſt thou theſe myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion? <hi>I know that thou believeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the later ſort, There is one place in his Book, where we have two of his <hi>pernicious</hi> errors together. The Doctor belike hath ſaid, that though a man ſhould reform his life, and be changed from vice to vertue, and that by hearing the word preached (This is the moſt I count he ſaies, and which may be exemplified in <hi>Herod,</hi> who <hi>heard John,</hi> and <hi>did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things</hi>), yet if there be not an habitual righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs infufed, it ſignifies nothing to regeneration. To this purpoſe is it only and altogether the Doctor ſpeaks. Hereupon this Gentleman breaks out and <hi>challenges</hi> him before his <hi>own party</hi> (as he ſpeaks) and before the <hi>world,</hi> for contradicting the Scripture <hi>[He that doeth Righteouſneſs is born of God],</hi> and then charges him with <hi>Pelagianiſm.</hi> He profeſſes he is in <hi>earneſt,</hi> and that this is <hi>rank Pelagianiſm,</hi> that the Doctor allows ſo much to be done without ſaving grace. I have the more reaſon to be moved at this, becauſe a certain perſon of quality, and of a ready judgement having this Author by him, turned me to this place, as if the Doctor was much to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; when I muſt needs ſay, that this Gentleman hath no where expoſed himſelf ſo much in his Book as here, where he endeavours to expoſe the Doctor. There is no man that reads practical Divines, that lay down characters of the truly godly man, the ſound Believer, and how far the Hypocrite may go, but does know they ſpeak commonly as the Doctor
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62274:49"/>does, and there are few, one would think, ſo inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate or raw, but ſhould alſo know here how to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh ſo eaſily, as between the <hi>matter</hi> of what is done, and the <hi>manner</hi> of the performance. Good works may be conſidered <hi>quoad operis ſubſtamtiam,</hi> or <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad modum quo ordinaniur id vuam aevernam.</hi> There is no good act (no not the leaſt that can be done) is performed in that manner as it ought, or as it is required to be accepted in order to ſalvation, but a man muſt be <hi>born of God</hi> according to <hi>his</hi> text, and have the aſſiſtance of the Spirit: But for the <hi>matter</hi> of the work (or of our duty) this Author muſt conſider better, that the Regenerate and Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penerate are alike as to that. <hi>One</hi> can hear, and pray, and give alms, and abſtain from evil as well as the <hi>Other;</hi> and many times the veryeſt Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite pretends moſt. Nay, what ſaies this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to <hi>Socrates, Ariſtides, Epimomdas, Plato, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tark, Cato?</hi> What ſaies he to <hi>Almanzor</hi> that <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met in</hi> Einperor, whoſe life is ſet out by Sir <hi>Walter Rayleigh</hi> in a little Book for ſuch ſingular vertues, eſpecially as to his goodneſs and righteouſneſs, that I find him not paralleld by any Chriſtian. Will this Author cenſure Sir <hi>Walter</hi> for a <hi>Pelagian,</hi> for ſuch a narration? or will he make me one, if I believe it? Or will he come over here, and when he hath placed ſuch in a <hi>ſtate of Nature,</hi> and ſo out of a <hi>ſtate of Grace,</hi> will he allow an Heathen or Mahometan to be a <hi>regeherate</hi> perſon? Hath the Gentleman read <hi>Ruiz,</hi> or one ſuch a kind of Schoolman as he, all over? Let him ſee when they have denied againſt <hi>pelagius</hi> all ability in man to do any thing, even but
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62274:49"/>to give an occaſion (which is <hi>active</hi> and not <hi>paſſive</hi> only) to infuſe in us their juſtifying grace, whether they are alſo ignorant of ſome ſuch diſtinction. It is no <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> in the Schools, to ſay a man can do many things <hi>civily, morally</hi> good, through the power of nature, education, cuſtome, for company ſake, for glory: but it is ſo, to ſay he can do any thing without preventing grace, <hi>in order to his juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> There is no need therefore of ſuch vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence, nor of any ſuch expreſſions he uſes other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>[I will deſire the Doctor to conſider whether the Father of lies be not the repreſentative of ſuch ſhameful Writers, as he is the example of].</hi> Theſe kind of words are not well. There is a great deal of acrimony, I ſee, with a little truth mixt methinks, like the fire and hail that ran together in one of the Egyptian Plagues, in the Books of many late riſing adverſaries to this learned pious and reverend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It were happy if the opprobrious words of the prejudicate, would make thewiſe mend their faults. It were well alſo if ſuch an inconſiderate confident piece of elation of mind (as here indeed is) be but repreſſed with the ſhame and bluſhes of another. <hi>Let the righteous ſmite me, it ſhall be a kindneſs, and let him reprove me, it ſhall be an oyle, and not break my head.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62274:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of Dr. <hi>Owen's</hi> Book of Juſtification, and of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> and St. <hi>James,</hi> and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs upon his account.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving ſaid this <hi>for</hi> the Doctor, I have a little now alſo to ſay <hi>to</hi> him. I was reading his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Book of Juſtification, when this Author came to my hands, and I had thought of making ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon it. I am not ſatisfied with what he hath offered for the reconciliation of St. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> on that ſubject. This is the reaſon I ſuppoſe (that is the moſt ſolid) why ſo many do chooſe here of late to go with the <hi>mediocrian,</hi> or ſteer the <hi>middle way,</hi> in that point. I perceive that Dr. <hi>Tully</hi> with our firſt Reformed Divines, and this excellent Doctor, are for diſtinguiſhing of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification,</hi> but will not let us, by no means, diſtinguiſh of <hi>Works</hi> for the reconciliation of the Apoſtles. I do wonder at this. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> do both agree, that we are juſtified by Faith. The one ſaies, <hi>we conclude that a man is juſtified by Faith;</hi> and the other ſaies alſo, it is <hi>by Faith:</hi> Their ſeeming difference is only about works, when one ſaies <hi>by Faith without Works,</hi> and the other, <hi>by Faith and Works alſo.</hi> And how then comes it to paſs that we muſt not diſtinguiſh of <hi>Works,</hi> but of <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> to compoſe the difficulty? I will offer the Doctor therefore here one Argument, under his favour, which ſhall be but one, and that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62274:50"/>not as others have, (ſo far as I know) for then it were like he had already weighed it. It is this. That Juſtification which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, is that Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication which we have in that Text of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>believed, and it was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Or, That Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlification <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, is that Imputation of Faith for righteouſneſs which is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Geneſis.</hi> That Juſtification which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, is that Juſtification which we have in that Text in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> Or, is that Imputation of Faith for Righteouſneſs, as is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Geneſis. Therefore</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> juſtification, and St. <hi>James</hi> juſtification are the ſame Juſtification. Again, That <hi>Faith</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, is the Faith that is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> or the ſame Faith as was impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Abraham</hi> for righteouſneſs in that place. That Faith which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of is the ſame Faith which is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Or the ſame Faith that was imputed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for righteouſneſs in that place. <hi>Therefore</hi> the faith that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, and the faith which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, is the ſame faith alſo. And when the <hi>Faith</hi> is the ſame, and the <hi>Juſtification</hi> the ſame, we muſt diſtinguiſh of <hi>Works</hi> then out of queſtion, to reconcile theſe Scriptures. Of Works then let us diſtinguiſh; and the diſtinction is this. There are Works which are inconſiſtent with Grace and Pardon, ſo that if we had them, we ſhould have no need of Chriſt's righteouſneſs or ſacrifice, but the doing of them would make the reward to be of debt, or make life to be due out of diſtrict juſtice, <hi>(He
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62274:51"/>that doeth them ſhall live in them</hi>), That is, Works which the Law requires unto Juſtification. And theſe are the Works St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which he alleadges why we are not juſtified by theſe Works is, becauſe no man hath them. This is that which he apparently urges (for he aſcends in his diſpute from the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> to the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which concerns both Jew and Gentile) in his three firſt Chapters to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſo that if any man be juſtified, it muſt be <hi>without</hi> them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we conclude (ſaies he) that by faith <hi>without them</hi> (that is without having them) a man is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. There are then Works alſo which are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with Pardon and Mercy though we have them, ſo that when we have done theſe, we do need the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and ſatisfaction of our Redeemer to cover their imperfection, and for acceptation of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, no leſs than if we had Faith alone without any, and theſe are Works of ſincerity required of us in the Goſpel. It is no wayes derogatory, I ſay, to Gods Grace and Chriſts Merits, for a man to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by theſe works, any more than to be juſtified by Faith alone, in regard to Debt or Merit, upon which account St. <hi>Paul</hi> excludes works in his Diſputation. It is <hi>of theſe Works</hi> I muſt ſay, (as the Apoſtle ſaies it is <hi>of Faith) that it may be of Grace.</hi> And theſe are the Works St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, when he ſaies, <hi>By Faith and Works alſo;</hi> that is all one as by a <hi>Faith working by Love</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> words otherwhere. And the being juſtified by <hi>Faith working by Love,</hi> or by a Faith productive of Works, or by theſe <hi>Works and Faith</hi> alſo (which being ſuch Works as fall ſhort
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62274:51"/>of the Law, and do need grace and forgiveneſs for their acceptation with God) is all one with St <hi>Pauls</hi> by Faith <hi>without works of the Law,</hi> or without ſuch as the Law requires unto juſtification. Thus are <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi> reconciled. I will advance hence then my former argument. That juſtification by Faith without works which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, is that Juſtification, or that Imputation of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith for righteouſneſs, which is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Geneſis.</hi> That juſtification by Works and Faith alſo, which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, is that Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication or that Imputation of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith for righteouſneſs, which is ſpoken of in that Text in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis. Therefore</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> juſtification by faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, and St. <hi>James</hi> juſtification by faith and works alſo, or <hi>by works and not by faith only,</hi> is the ſame in the two Apoſtles. The <hi>medium</hi> upon which all three Syllogiſms depend, is the Apoſtles citing the ſame Text, both of them, for that which either of them aſſert, while one ſaies <hi>by faith without works,</hi> and the other <hi>by works and not by faith only.</hi> The <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> and <hi>minor</hi> therefore in all three are undeniable; and in the concluſion of the laſt, I am ſure the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and I ſhall agree together.</p>
               <p>I have another thing to offer to the thoughts of the Dr. that whereas he tells us of a Commutation between Chriſt and us in his taking upon him our ſins, and our partaking of his righteouſneſs, I do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend this expreſſion and doctrine to be Chriſtian, holy and good, according to the ſenſe of that Text, <hi>He was made ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> and the like places:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62274:52"/>But only there is a difference to be put between the uſe of the notion againſt the <hi>Socinians</hi> in the point of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and the uſe of it againſt the <hi>Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creans</hi> in the point of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> I do believe ſuch a Commutation as the Dr. ſpeaks of, is neceſſary to that great work which Chriſt undertook for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as it concerns the whole world in the procuring Reconciliation and Life for all upon the terms of the Redeemer; for if he had not taken on him our ſins, to ſuffer in our behalf (which is his <hi>being made ſin for us</hi>) and fulfilled the whole Law alſo for us, that God might without diſhonour to him as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, diſpenſe with it, ſo as to impute to us our faith and imperfect obedience for righteouſneſs (which is our being <hi>made the righteouſneſs of God in him</hi>) there would have been no ſatisfaction offered, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no Reconciliation or Redemption: But as for ſuch a Commutation in the point of Juſtification, which concerns particular Believers, I am yet to learn what to make of it from this Reverend perſon. To enquire then to the bottom, the foundation of this <hi>Commutation,</hi> is laid (I ſee) by him in the Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union between Chriſt and his Members, which muſt pertain therefore only to ſuch, and that as a fruit or effect of the Spirit of Chriſt given to them (if it be ſo) to that end: When this indeed is a thing that does not belong at all to the operation of the <hi>Third</hi> perſon of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> but to the work of the <hi>Son,</hi> and the arbitrary ordination of the <hi>Father.</hi> Whatſoever influence Chriſt hath upon the ſoul as our Head by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt; or whatſoever is an effect of the Spirit when once given
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62274:52"/>for uniting us to him, it muſt have this Union for its ground or foundation: But whatſoever ariſes to us from Chriſt another way, and is no effect of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it may not be aſcribed without contradiction to that ſpring from whence it comes not. The Dr. judges right, that ſuch a Communication with Chriſt cannot indeed be rationally thought on, but we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> preſently which is the ground of it: But there is a double Union between Chriſt and us. The one is by <hi>taking</hi> upon him our <hi>Nature,</hi> and the other by <hi>giving</hi> us his <hi>Spirit.</hi> The bleſſed Commutation the Dr. ſpeaks of, does not depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Union which we have with him by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of his <hi>Spirit;</hi> for this indeed is no waies any effect thereof: But it does depend on the Union which he hath with us in taking upon him our <hi>Fleſh. Foraſmuch then as the children are partakers of fleſh and blood, he alſo took part of the ſame.</hi> Again, <hi>He took not on him the nature of Angels, but he took on him the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> and in that <hi>ſeed</hi> our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and as he took our nature, he took on him our ſins; for he took our nature only to this end, that he might redeem Man, when the Angels whoſe nature he took not, were not redeemed. <hi>Wherefore when he cometh into the world, he ſaith, ſacrifice and offering thou wouldſt not, but a body haſt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared me.</hi> A body is prepar'd for Chriſt, that he may be a ſacrifice to anſwer thoſe Types under the Law, which without him could ſignifie nothing, The Beaſt for the Propitiatory Sacrifice had the ſins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> laid on him; and this is exhibited in that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>John, Behold the Lamb of God that takes
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62274:53"/>away the ſins of the world:</hi> And of that in <hi>Peter, Who his own ſelf bare our ſins in his own body on the Tree.</hi> It is manifeſt then that this Commutation which conſiſts in Chriſt's taking upon him our ſins, that he might be a ſacrifice for them, and fulfilling the duty of the whole Law (which we were bound unto, but broke) to procure new terms, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance whereof we might be righteous, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted upon the account of his merits (which is his <hi>becoming ſin for us, that we might become the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God in him,</hi> as I have ſaid before, and have need to ſay again) does belong to that Union which Chriſt hath with Mankind, according to that Text in the <hi>Hebrews, He that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are of one;</hi> that is, of <hi>one fleſh,</hi> as appears by what follows; and not to that Union which he hath with his Members only, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Text in the <hi>Corinths, He that is joyned to the Lord is one ſpirit;</hi> that is, it belongs to that Union which is <hi>Hypoſtatical</hi> in Chriſt's taking our nature with the Divine Nature into one perſon, and not to that Union which is <hi>Myſtical,</hi> according to the ſuppoſition of the Dr. There is a diſtinction then to be remembred, which we have often in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and that is of <hi>Chriſt in the Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt in the Spirit.</hi> We muſt make a difference accordingly between what he did for us, as he was in the fleſh, and what he does for us <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> or by it. That which he did for us <hi>in the Fleſh</hi> (I ſpeak it indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely) muſt belong to <hi>All,</hi> for the fleſh he took, was the fleſh of <hi>All;</hi> and hence is he ſaid to <hi>die for All,</hi> to <hi>taſte Death for every man,</hi> to be a propitiation,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62274:53"/>not for <hi>our ſins only, but for the ſins of the world.</hi> That which he does for us <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> is peculiar to his <hi>Members,</hi> and the Elect to whom he gives it. I ſpeak of the Spirit as a principle of Union and Life in Chriſt, and not as Author of <hi>common</hi> giſts. I argue now. It is certain that the Righteouſneſs Chriſt performed, and the Sacrifice he made for us, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and made <hi>in the Fleſh.</hi> It is certain that in this Righteouſneſs and Sacrifice is contained all that he undertook in our behalf, as he ſuſtained our part in the work of his Mediation for Man's Redemption. It is certain that the Commutation the Dr. ſpeaks of, muſt be ſuppoſed unto Chriſt's ſuſtaining our part in this work. It is certain conſequently that this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, and the part Chriſt ſuſtained in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming this Righteouſneſs, and offering this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, does belong to <hi>Chriſt in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſo muſt be univerſal for all the world, and does not belong to <hi>Chriſt in the Spirit,</hi> to be appropriated to his <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Members</hi> only, which is this Learned Drs. apprehenſion throughout his Book. Let us diſtinguiſh then now at laſt between the <hi>Impetration</hi> of our Redemption, and all thoſe benefits we have by Chriſt, and the <hi>Application</hi> of them. The <hi>Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> belongs to Chriſt in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to Chriſt in the <hi>Spirit.</hi> (I mean by Impetration, obtaining by Sacrifice and Merit, and diſtinguiſh it from Interceſſion). Chriſt took our <hi>Fleſh</hi> to <hi>procure</hi> our Redemption; he gives us his <hi>Spirit</hi> to <hi>apply</hi> it. Now I have this notion to offer the Dr. under his correction if I be out, and under his candour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, if it be light; that this bleſſed Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62274:54"/>he ſpeaks of, and rightly magnifies, does go to the <hi>Impetration</hi> of our Redemption, and the benefits we have by Chriſt, and not to the <hi>Application.</hi> If this Commutation between Chriſt and us, of his Righteouſneſs for our ſins, did go to (or was made in) the Application, I ſee not how any more than one man could have it. If Chriſt makes the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſo takes his ſins, and gives him his Righteouſneſs in exchange, this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt muſt now be <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> cannot have it. It muſt not be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conceived ſure, that this Commutation is made with particular perſons, or that it does go into the Application, but that it goes into the Impetration of thoſe benefits we have by Chriſt, which being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for all upon condition, there is no particular perſon but by the performing that condition alike may (and by that means only can) enjoy them, one with another. To make this quite clear, there is but one cloud to be removed, which does (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) hang on the mind of moſt, in thinking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more of the Spirit's <hi>Application</hi> of what Chriſt hath done for us, or of his Merits and Righteouſneſs to the ſoul, than there is. But this is all that I am able to underſtand of this Application; to wit, that the Spirit by his grace enables us to perform the conditions upon which theſe benefits are procured for us; and ſo they become ours, and the Merits and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt are ſaid to be ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe effects. They are ours for the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of theſe benefits,</hi> but they cannot be ours in <hi>themſelves,</hi> that is, not ours in regard to the <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62274:54"/>What. Chriſt did for us in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> was to reconcile our ſalvation to God's glory, and the ends of Government: What Chriſt does in the <hi>Spirit</hi> is to reconcile our ſpirits to what God requires of us, and ſo to qualifie us for our poſſeſſion of the benefits which he hath purchaſed in the fleſh. The benefits are ours, and we enjoy them as being impetrated for us upon that condition, which through the Spirit (given for the Application) we perform, and Chriſt's Righteouſneſs and Merits being ours in regard to theſe effects it may be ſaid to be <hi>imputed</hi> to us if our Divines pleaſe. If there be conceived any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation with Chriſt of his Righteouſneſs for our ſins, or any imputation of it unto us any otherwiſe than thus in regard to the effects, I underſtand it not. The principal effect of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs and Sacrifice (which both together making up ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to God for man's ſin, God is reconciled, and comes to new terms) is the obtaining the Law of Grace for us, according to which we may be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or <hi>made the Righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt,</hi> in the Scripture phraſe (See my <hi>Middle</hi> Paper of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants in the ſix firſt leaves), and upon this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as the condition performed, all other of the effects or benefits depend. In the Application it is true, that we have the benefits, but from whence do they come? It is not from any act of ours, we are not our own Benefactors; nor from any work of the Spirit. That we do, is the performing the condition, and that the Spirit does, is the ſupplying us with grace to do it: But the condition is not the cauſe of the benefits, only <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> which being
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62274:55"/>put, the benefits flow to us by vertue of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, from the merit of what Chriſt hath done. <hi>Many</hi> (ſaies Mr. <hi>Truman</hi>) <hi>make this their ſtrong hold, that faith alone is the receptive grace, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and ſincere obedience: but there is no ſuch thing as receiving Righteouſneſs, Juſtification, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Juſtification, right to Heaven, Righteouſneſs,</hi> cometh <hi>on men. The free gift came upon all to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. By the offence of one, judgment came upon all to condemnation. As condemnation cometh upon men without any act of receiving it, it is a reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy from the Law upon diſobedience: So Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, right to Heaven, is a reſultancy from a Law-promiſe, the condition being performed.</hi> This I look on not only as <hi>pretty,</hi> but in regard to what I apply it very <hi>ſolid.</hi> It is from the Covenant-promiſe, or through the Law of grace immediately, and ſo from the Impetration of Chriſt and his Merits at laſt (or ultimately) that the benefits <hi>come on us,</hi> and all that we do towards it, is only our performing the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Cometh this bleſſedneſs then on the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion only, or on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion alſo?</hi> It is to be obſerved a little farther, that when the Scripture ſpeaks any thing of this Commutation, we find it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed only to God and Chriſt, and that as a thing paſt and done, and never to the work of the Spirit, which is ſtill a doing. It is ſaid therefore that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid <hi>the iniquities of us all,</hi> or made all our ſins to meet on Chriſt, in the perſon of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that Chriſt <hi>took</hi> them, <hi>bare our ſins,</hi> with the like expreſſions: But I read nor a word of ſuch a work as is ſtill to be done, which the Holy Ghoſt's
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62274:55"/>were, if it belonged to him. It muſt be conceived therefore that God and Chriſt in their everlaſting tranſactions between them, about the redemption of Man, agreed upon this matter of Commutation, which (however the Dr. expreſſes it) in the root, is Chriſt's undertaking to ſtand in our ſtead according to the Law of his Mediation; which Law he perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this buſineſs actually was accompliſhed, and we have the <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> declared on the Croſs: So that be it whatſoever it will, it does go, or did go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Impetration, it cannot go into the Application of our Repemplion. To come home then quite to the Dr. How Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is imputed to us in regard to the <hi>Impetration</hi> of the benefits we have from him, or how it is made ours in regard to the <hi>Effects impetrated,</hi> as thoſe effects are purchaſed by it upon <hi>condition,</hi> I underſtand; but how it is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, or made ours in the Application by the Spirit in any effect, or in the effect of Juſtification, any otherwiſe than other effects, I have had my eyes opened ſo long about this point, as I begin to ſee at laſt with much adoe, nothing of it. Adoption, Salvation, and other benefits, as well as Juſtification, are effects of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, or of Chriſt's purchaſe, and when we believe and perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, we receive Adoption, and have a right to Salvation as well as to be Juſtified. Adoption is by faith, Salvation by faith, Juſtification by faith. As faith concurs to the one, it does to the other. Here only is the deceit. Juſtification is Gods accounting a perſon righteous, and this being upon the account of Chriſts righteouſneſs, the underſtanding is entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62274:56"/>as if we were made righteous by his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſome way, as muſt render us to be juſtified otherwiſe by it, than ſaved. There never was any diſpute about the imputation of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to our Adoption and Salvation, and yet it is a certain truth, that it is imputed to us in regard to theſe effects, as in regard to Juſtification. The righteouſneſs of Chriſt then does concur to our Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Salvation, <hi>ſub genere cauſae efficientis,</hi> as the meritorious procuring cauſe of them: if it concur any otherwiſe unto Juſtification, that is <hi>ſub genere cauſae formalis</hi> alſo, as the <hi>formal reaſon</hi> no leſs than the <hi>procuring cauſe</hi> of it, it is a matter (I muſt confeſs) of my Admiration; and I muſt crave of the Doctor farther inſtruction, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to accept this ſlender endeavour of mine for his own ſatisfaction. <hi>And the third Captain of fifty went up, and came and bowed before</hi> Elijah <hi>and beſought him, and ſaid unto him, O man of God, I pray thee — And he aroſe and went down with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have many other thoughts in my mind to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Doctor, or this Author, which I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, for I remember that the Gentleman hath a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part to come out, that he intends more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly againſt the Doctor. I will therefore ſtay a while upon ſuch matters that are already propoſed, and ſee if he performs his intention; and it will be then time enough (if it be like alſo to do good, and be fit) to confer a few more notions with him. For I like my man much for his <hi>Natural
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62274:56"/>parts,</hi> and <hi>Free-Divinity:</hi> as I muſt note him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for deficient in his <hi>Ethicks</hi> and <hi>Civility,</hi> ſo long as he hath to do with ſuch an Adverſary. I cannot commend him for this uſage of the Doctor; who is one I muſt confeſs for my own part, that I value for his Worth, I love for his Courteſie, I am pleaſed with for his Candour, and I think my ſelf happy, if at any time I get but a little of his Company.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:57"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:57"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEaſt I ſhould not have occaſion (or leaſt I ſhould not take it, if I have) to write again upon theſe matters, I muſt tell you of ſome things I find wanting. I have not commended this Ingenious Perſon for his very apt Expoſition of ſome Texts, as I think he deſerves, if I had examined them well enough to do it. Again, I have not declared my ſcope in the diſcourſe I have about the <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> man, in the beginning of the Book. If one imagine my ſcope to be only to confute this Author, he will make little of me, and leſs of himſelf. My ſcope is not to invalidate the Interpretation he brings, which I acknowledge fair: nor to advance the other, which I impute to the <hi>Friendly Debater</hi> (becauſe I took my firſt hint from him) but in the cultivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it any man may ſee in whoſe mind it is harbored: Nor do I confirm the Doctors againſt this Authors oppoſition, to prefer it before either: But I do impartially endeavour the elucidation of the place, as a ſearcher after Truth, to this end, that he who hath the beſt faculty of diſcerning, may have all the light I have to his own, to make judgement. This is not the manner ordinarily of others. And this I do alſo, that by ſuch indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of mine, I may put ſome diſcountenance upon the over-peremptorineſs of this worthy Young man, who, when he ſees his own Notion to be reaſonable,
<pb facs="tcp:62274:58"/>does forget that the Doctors, or mine, may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable alſo. Another thing is this, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt the ſalvability of Heathen [becauſe Salvation is by Chriſt, and they have, no Faith in Chriſt, and no knowledge of him] I have <hi>omitted</hi> ſomething at <hi>large,</hi> that I muſt give you <hi>intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of here in a <hi>little.</hi> Salvation is by Chriſt, I have determined (I ſuppoſe well) in that he hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Law of Grace by which we are governed, and ſhall be judged; and ſo long as the Heathen, or all the world, are under that government of grace as well as we, Salvation muſt come to them upon the ſame account of Chriſt, as it does to us, if any of them perform the Condition. And what if the Heathen knows not this, that it is Chriſt that hath procured this remedying Law for us, and them, yet is that nothing, as to the truth of the thing, for ſo it is, and thoſe that live well, have the benefit of it. If a ranſom be gathered for the Slave at <hi>Algiers,</hi> he is freed from his ſlavery no leſs for that, becauſe he knowes not the Friends that did it. The Diſciples were partakers of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Chriſt, when they knew nothing of his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice till after his death and reſurrection. And what did the Jews know, if the Diſciples knew no more? For Faith then, As there is a threefold <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of the Covenant of grace according to the ſtate of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> according to what I have ſaid: So is there a threefold <hi>Faith</hi> in regard to theſe three Adminiſtrations of it. Faith is diverſified according to its Objects, or the Revelations which man has from God. I have not
<pb facs="tcp:62274:58"/>room here for Explanation. Though a Heathen hath not that Faith <hi>as</hi> is required of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> under the <hi>third</hi> promulgation of the Covenant, or <hi>was</hi> of the <hi>Jew</hi> under the <hi>ſecond,</hi> yet hath he ſuch a faith as belongs to the <hi>firſt,</hi> and ſo long as that <hi>faith</hi> he has, does <hi>work by love,</hi> or by ſincere obedience to God, it will juſtifie him, as ours will. And this is the meaning of that Text, <hi>But now is the righteouſneſs of God revealed from faith to faith:</hi> The righteouſneſs of God is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of this Covenant, which hath been ever a foot, as in my Paper of the <hi>Covenants</hi> I ſhew, and <hi>from faith to faith,</hi> is from the faith which was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond,</hi> to that which is now required in the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> Promulgution of it. I have not ſaid this full enough, but it is neceſſary to be intimated; And in the the room that is left I muſt give notice, that I let theſe ſheets be a ſticht Book, that my Papers of the <hi>Middle Way</hi> may be bound up with them, becauſe they are of the ſame Nature. There was four of theſe Papers, about five ſheets a piece. Of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Of <hi>Juſtification;</hi> Of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> Law and <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and Of <hi>Perfection.</hi> They are compleat none of them without one another, for what I found wanting in one Paper, I took liberty to ſupply in the next, though of another Subject. <hi>My work</hi> is to dig the Metal, the <hi>Refiner</hi> is another Trade. The Point of Juſtification that got out firſt from me, is not perfectly ſtated till the Reader hath read both the ſix and ſeven firſt leaves of the <hi>Covenants,</hi> and the beginning of <hi>Perfection.</hi> Theſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, I entituled <hi>Mediocria,</hi> and from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in
<pb facs="tcp:62274:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe preſent Sheets I do once or twice call thoſe who are for the Middle way in theſe Points, <hi>Mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> There are ſeveral places in them very needful for him to ſee that reads theſe preſent <hi>Diſquiſitions;</hi> but ſix or ſeven firſt leaves of the Paper of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> (before I come to treat thoſe Subjects themſelves) I ſuppoſe to be moſt neceſſary; though the laſt Point I think moſt maturely ſtated. Thoſe twenty ſheets, and theſe fourteen together will make a ſufficient bound Book.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 58. line 31. for <hi>diſcernings</hi> read <hi>deſervings.</hi> p. 92. l. ult. for <hi>dy</hi> r. <hi>body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62274:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
